<chapter id="gramps-mainwin"> 

<!--
	  User Manual for Gramps - a GTK+/GNOME based genealogy program

	  Copyright (C) 2003-2005  Alexander Roitman

	  This document is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify
	  it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by
	  the Free Software Foundation; either version 2 of the License, or
	  (at your option) any later version.

	  This document is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
	  but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
	  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
	  GNU General Public License for more details.

	  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
	  along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software
	  Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
-->

<!-- $Id$ -->

  <title>Main Window</title> 
 
  <para>
    When you open a database (either existing or brand new), the
    following window is displayed:
  </para>
 
<!-- ==== Figure: Main Window  ==== -->

  <figure id="mainwin-fig" pgwide="1"> 
    <title>GRAMPS Main Window</title> 
    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="figures/mainwin.png" format="PNG" width="500" depth="352" scale="70"/>
        </imageobject>
	<textobject> 
	  <phrase>
            Shows GRAMPS main window. Contains titlebar, menubar, 
	    toolbar, sidebar, display area, statusbar, progressbar, and
	    scrollbars. Menubar contains File, Edit, View, Go, Bookmarks, 
	    Reports, Tools, Settings, and Help menus.  
          </phrase>
	</textobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </figure>
	
<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

  <para>
    The &app; window contains the following elements: 
  </para>

  <variablelist>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Menubar</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The menubar is located at the very top of the window (right
          below the window title) and provides access to all features
          of &app; through its menus.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Toolbar</term>
      <listitem>
        <para> 
          The toolbar is located immediately below the menubar.  The
          toolbar provides access to the most frequently used
          functions of &app;. The appearance of the toolbar can be
          adjusted in the <guilabel>Preferences</guilabel> dialog.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Progressbar</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The progressbar is located in the lower left corner of the
	  &app; window. It displays the progress of time consuming
	  operations, such as opening and saving large data bases,
	  importing and exporting to other formats, generating web
	  sites, etc.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Statusbar</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The statusbar is located to the right of the progressbar, on
          the very bottom of the &app; window.  It displays
          information about current &app; activity and contextual
          information about the menu items.  The behavior of the
          statusbar can be adjusted in
          <guilabel>Preferences</guilabel> dialog.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Display area</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The largest area in the center of the &app; window is the
	  display area.  It shows certain aspects of genealogical
	  information, depending on the currently selected View. The
	  following six Views are available in &app;:
  	    <itemizedlist>	
	      <listitem><para>People View, see <xref linkend="people-view"/></para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para>Family View, see <xref linkend="family-view"/></para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para>Pedigree View, see <xref linkend="pedigree-view"/></para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para>Sources View, see <xref linkend="sources-view"/></para></listitem>
  	      <listitem><para>Places View, see <xref linkend="places-view"/></para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para>Media View, see <xref linkend="media-view"/></para></listitem>
 	    </itemizedlist>
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist> 

<!-- ================ Main Window Subsection  -->

  <sect1 id="gramps-views">
    <title>Views</title>
    <para>
      Views are the various ways to display different aspects of
      genealogical information. It is best to split the relevant
      information display into smaller categories, uniform in context
      and modality; since it is very broad and non-uniform in both
      context and modality. Each View represents such a split and
      displays a certain portion of overall available
      information. Before reviewing the detailed description of
      available Views, you will be guided through the ways of
      switching between the Views.
    </para> 

<!-- ================ Main Window Sub-subsection  -->

    <sect2 id="view-modes">
      <title>Switching Views and Viewing Modes</title>
      <para>
        Depending on the state of the <menuchoice>
	<guimenu>View</guimenu><guimenuitem>Sidebar</guimenuitem>
	</menuchoice> menu item, the View could be switched either in
	the sidebar or in the notebook tabs in the top part of the
	window.
      </para>

      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
          <term>
            To switch the View while in a Sidebar mode, 
	    click on the desired sidebar icon.
          </term>
	  <listitem>

<!-- ==== Figure: Sidebar Mode ==== -->

	    <figure id="side-nofilt-fig"> 
	      <title>Sidebar Viewing Mode</title> 
	      <screenshot>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="figures/mainwin.png" format="PNG" width="500" depth="352" scale="75"/>
                   </imageobject>
  	           <textobject> 
	             <phrase>Shows sidebar viewing mode.</phrase>
  	           </textobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
            </figure>

 <!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

	  </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
          <term>
            To switch the View while in a Tabbed mode, 
	    click on the desired notebook tab.
          </term>
	  <listitem>

 <!-- ==== Figure: Tabbed Notebook Mode ==== -->
 	  
            <figure id="noside-nofilt-fig"> 
	      <title>Tabbed Viewing Mode</title> 
	      <screenshot>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="figures/noside-nofilt.png" format="PNG" width="500" depth="393" scale="75"/>
                  </imageobject>
	          <textobject> 
	            <phrase>Shows tabbed viewing mode.</phrase>
  	          </textobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
            </figure>
<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->
	  </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para>
        To switch between sidebar and tabbed viewing modes, choose
	<menuchoice> <guimenu>View</guimenu>
	<guimenuitem>Sidebar</guimenuitem> </menuchoice> from the
	&app; menu.
      </para>
    
    </sect2>

<!-- ================ Main Window Sub-subsection  -->

    <sect2 id="people-view">
      <title>People View</title>
      <para>
        When &app; first opens a database, the View is set to the
	People View (<xref linkend="side-nofilt-fig"/> and <xref
	linkend="noside-nofilt-fig"/>). The People View lists
	individuals whose data is stored in the database.
      </para>
      <para> 
        The individuals are arranged in a tree-like structure,
        according to their family names. Every family name is a node
        of the tree. Clicking the arrow on the left of the node will
        toggle its expansion state. When expanded, the node's content
        is listed in the window. When collapsed, the content is
        rolled up and not visible.  All the data is still
        intact. It is just not being displayed.
      </para>
      <para>
        The People View, in its default state, displays people's
        <guilabel>Names</guilabel>, &app; <guilabel>ID</guilabel>
        numbers, <guilabel>Gender</guilabel>, and their
        <guilabel>Birth</guilabel> and <guilabel>Death
        dates</guilabel>.  The list can be ordered by any field.
      </para>
	
      <tip id="columns-tip">
        <title>Order list by selected column</title>
	<para>
          To order list by the Birth date, click on the
	  <guilabel>Birth date</guilabel> column heading. To order
	  list in reverse (descending) order, click one more time on
	  the desired column heading.
        </para> 
      </tip>

      <para>
        The columns of the view may be added, removed, or reordered in
	a <guilabel>Column Editor Dialog</guilabel>, see <xref
	linkend="column-editor-fig"/>. Only checked columns will be
	shown in the view. To change their order, drag any column to
	its desired location inside the editor. Clicking
	<guibutton>OK</guibutton> will reflect the changes in the
	People View. To invoke <guilabel>Column Editor
	Dialog</guilabel>, choose
	<menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Column
	Editor</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
      </para>

      <tip id="columns-tip2">
        <title>Other Views</title>
	<para>
          The <guilabel>Column Editor</guilabel> is available and
	  works in the same way for all list views, not only People
	  View.
        </para> 
      </tip>

<!-- ==== Figure: Enabled Filter ==== -->

      <figure id="column-editor-fig"> 
	<title>Column Editor Dialog</title> 
	<screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/column-editor.png" format="PNG" width="444" depth="437" scale="75"/>
            </imageobject>
	    <textobject> 
	      <phrase>Shows column editor dialog. </phrase>
  	    </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>

<!-- ================ Main Window Sub-sub-subsection  -->

      <sect3 id="filters">
        <title>Filters</title>
        <para>
          Genealogical databases may contain huge numbers of people.
	  Since the long lists are hard for humans to manage, &app;
	  provides a convenient way to limit the scope of browsing by
	  using the filter. To save screen space, filter controls may
	  be hidden, depending on the state of <menuchoice>
	  <guimenu>View</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Filter</guimenuitem>
	  </menuchoice> menu item.
        </para>
	  
<!-- ==== Figure: Enabled Filter ==== -->

	<figure id="side-filt-fig"> 
  	  <title>Filter Controls Displayed</title> 
	  <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="figures/side-filt.png" format="PNG" width="500" depth="352" scale="75"/>
              </imageobject>
	      <textobject> 
	        <phrase>Shows filter controls.</phrase>
  	      </textobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>

<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

	<para>
          When &app; opens a database, the filter is set to the
	  trivial filter called <guilabel>Entire Database</guilabel>,
	  i.e. no filtering is in effect. To choose a filter, use the
	  pop-up <guilabel>Filter</guilabel> menu above the people's
	  list. Once the filter is chosen, click the
	  <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> button in the upper right
	  corner of the window. The filtering will take effect upon
	  clicking the <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> button.
         </para>

	<para>
          GRAMPS provides a way to create cutom filters to easily show
      specific parts of the database. This is achieved using the 
      <guilabel>Custom Filter Editor</guilabel> in the <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Tools</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Utilities</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> menu. See <xref linkend="tools-util-cfe" />
         </para>

	 <tip id="filt-tip">
           <title>Example filter use</title>
	   <para>
             To show males only, choose <guilabel>Males</guilabel>
	     filter, then click the <guibutton>Apply</guibutton>
	     button. To cancel any filtering, set the filter to
	     <guilabel>Entire Database</guilabel> and then click the
	     <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> button.
            </para>
	  </tip>
	  
	  <note id="filt-note">
 	    <title>Filtering is persistent</title>
	    <para> 
              Even if the filter controls are not displayed
	      (<menuchoice> <guimenu>View</guimenu>
	      <guimenuitem>Filter</guimenuitem> </menuchoice> menu
	      item is unchecked), the filtering might still be in
	      place. In other words, the visibility of the filter
	      controls is not related to the actual filtering imposed
	      on the list.
            </para>
	    <para>
              This may be a cause of confusion, when you enable the
	      filtering and then remove the controls from the
	      display. If in doubt, enable the display of filter
	      controls by checking <menuchoice>
	      <guimenu>View</guimenu>
	      <guimenuitem>Filter</guimenuitem> </menuchoice> menu
	      item and check what kind of filtering is currently set.
            </para> 
	  </note>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>
      
<!-- ================ Main Window Sub-subsection  -->

      <sect2 id="family-view">
        <title>Family View</title>
	<para>
          Family View displays the family information of a currently
	  selected (or Active) person. Specifically, this view shows
	  the relationships (e.g. marriages, partnerships, etc.) of the
	  active person, his/her parents (or step parents, or
	  guardians, etc), and his/her children (could be step
	  children, adopted children, etc.).
        </para>
	
<!-- ==== Figure: Family View ==== -->

	<figure id="family-fig"> 
 	  <title>Family View</title> 
	  <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="figures/family.png" format="PNG" width="500" depth="352" scale="75"/>
              </imageobject>
	      <textobject> 
	        <phrase>Shows Family View.</phrase>
	      </textobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>

	<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

	<para>
          The Active person's data is in the list box in the upper
	  left corner of the window. Directly below it, another box
	  lists the Spouse's data, for each relationship of Active
	  person (can be more than one).  The double-arrow button to
	  the right of the Active person list box allows you to
	  exchange the currently selected spouse (Current spouse) with
	  the Active person. Double-clicking on the Active person
	  allows the editing of Active person's data. Double-clicking
	  on the Current spouse allows you to edit their relationship
	  information. Shift-clicking on the Current spouse allows the
	  editing of the Current spouse's data.
        </para>
        <para> 
           To add a new relationship, use one of the two upper buttons
          to the right of the spouse box. Click the top one to add a
          new person to a database and to the new relationship. Click
          the middle one to add a person already existing in the
          database to the new relationship.  To remove Current spouse,
          click the lowest button (<guibutton>-</guibutton>) to the
          right of the spouse box. Note that removing a spouse from
          the relationship does not remove the person from the
          database. Most of these functions are also available by
          right-clicking into the spouse box and selecting an
          appropriate item from the context menu.
        </para>
	<para>
          The parents of both the Active person and the Current spouse
	  are listed in the corresponding list boxes in the right-hand
	  part of the window (Active person's parents on top, Current
	  spouse parents on the bottom). Both list boxes have a set of
	  three buttons on their right side. The
	  <guibutton>+</guibutton> and <guibutton>-</guibutton>
	  buttons allow you to add and remove parents of the Active
	  person and the Current spouse, respectively. Clicking the
	  right arrow button makes the family in the corresponding
	  list box an active family.  That is, it makes the selected
	  Father the Active person, and the selected Mother the
	  Current spouse. Most of these functions are also available
	  by right-clicking into the parent box and selecting an
	  appropriate item from the context menu.
        </para>
	<para>
          The bottom list box displays children of the Active person
	  and the Current Spouse. The Children's list can be ordered
	  by the Birth date in the usual way of clicking on the
	  <guilabel>Birth date</guilabel> column header. In addition
	  to the <guilabel>Name</guilabel>, <guilabel>ID</guilabel>,
	  <guilabel>Gender</guilabel>, and <guilabel>Birth
	  date</guilabel> columns, the list includes a
	  <guilabel>Status</guilabel> column. The pair of status words
	  reflect the relationship between the child and his
	  Father/Mother (such as Birth, Adoption,
	  etc.). <guilabel>Column Editor Dialog</guilabel> can be used
	  to change column arrangement.  Four buttons are available on
	  the right side of the children list box. The top (left
	  arrow) button makes the selected child the Active
	  person. The next two buttons add a new child to the family:
	  the upper one adds a new person to the database and to the
	  family, the lower one just adds a person existing in the
	  database to the family. Finally, the lowest
	  <guibutton>-</guibutton> button removes the selected child
	  from the family. Note that removing a child from the family
	  does not remove the person from the database. Most of these
	  functions are also available by right-clicking into the
	  children box and selecting an appropriate item from the
	  context menu.
        </para> 
	<para>
          The layout of the Family View can be switched from the
          left-to-right arrangement (shown above) to the top-to-bottom
          arrangement (shown below). This can be done in the
          <guilabel>Display</guilabel> section of the
          <guilabel>Preferences</guilabel> dialog. The top-to-bottom
          view has the same functionality as the left-to-right view.
        </para>

<!-- ==== Figure: Family View ==== -->

	<figure id="family-alt-fig"> 
	  <title>Alternative Family View</title> 
	  <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="figures/family-alt.png" format="PNG" width="500" depth="352" scale="75"/>
              </imageobject>
	      <textobject> 
	        <phrase>Shows Alternative Family View.</phrase>
  	      </textobject>
            </mediaobject> 
          </screenshot>
        </figure>

<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

      </sect2>

<!-- ================ Main Window Sub-subsection  -->
      <sect2 id="pedigree-view">
        <title>Pedigree View</title>

<!-- ==== Figure: Pedigree View ==== -->

	<figure id="pedigree-fig"> 
  	  <title>Pedigree View</title> 
	  <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="figures/pedigree.png" format="PNG" width="500" depth="352" scale="75"/>
              </imageobject>
	      <textobject> 
	        <phrase>Shows Pedigree View.</phrase>
 	      </textobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>

<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

	<para>

          The Pedigree View helps to visualize the place of the Active
	  person in the tree of his/her ancestors. The Pedigree View
	  shows four generations, going back in time from the Active
	  person <guilabel>1</guilabel> to his/her parents
	  <guilabel>2</guilabel>, to grandparents
	  <guilabel>3</guilabel>, to great-grandparents
	  <guilabel>4</guilabel>.  Each person is denoted by a box
	  bearing the person's name.  The two lines that converge on
	  the box represent ties with the person's Father (top line)
	  and mother (bottom line). Solid lines represent birth
	  relations, while dashed lines represent non-birth relations
	  (such as adoption, step-parenthood, guardianship, etc.).
	  When the mouse moves over the white box, it expands to
	  display the corresponding person's dates of birth and
	  death. When the mouse is placed over the family line, the
	  line becomes highlighted to indicate an active link:
	  double-clicking on the line makes the corresponding ancestor
	  the Active person. The display in that case is re-adjusted
	  to show four generations, starting from the newly selected
	  Active person.

        </para>
	
<!-- ==== Figure: Pedigree View ==== -->

	<figure id="pedigree-child-cut-fig"> 
	  <title>Children Menu</title> 
	  <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="figures/pedigree-child-cut.png" format="PNG" width="303" depth="195"/>
              </imageobject>
	      <textobject> 
	        <phrase>Shows Children Menu in Pedigree View.</phrase>
 	      </textobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>

<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

	<para>

          The left-hand side of the window shows the left arrow
	  button.  Upon clicking, the button expands to the menu
	  listing the children of the Active person. Selecting the
	  menu item makes the corresponding child the Active
	  person. The appearance of the children's names in the menu
	  serves to differentiate the "dead ends" of the tree from the
	  continuing branches as follows. The children who have
	  children appear in the menu in the boldface and italic
	  typeset, while the children without children ("dead ends")
	  appear in a regular font. If the Active person has a single
	  child, no menu will be displayed (since there is no choice)
	  and the child will become the Active person upon clicking
	  the arrow button.

       </para><para>

          The right-hand side of the window shows two right arrow
	  buttons.  When the top button is clicked, the Father of the
	  Active person becomes the Active person. Clicking the bottom
	  button makes the Mother of the Active person the Active
	  person. Again, the display is re-adjusted to show four
	  generations, starting from the newly selected Active person.

        </para> 

<!-- ==== Figure: Pedigree View ==== -->

	<figure id="pedigree-siblings-cut-fig"> 
 	  <title>Personal Context Menu</title> 
	  <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="figures/pedigree-siblings-cut.png" format="PNG" width="500" depth="253" scale="75"/>
              </imageobject>
	      <textobject> 
	        <phrase>Shows Context Menu in Pedigree View.</phrase>
 	      </textobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>

<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->
	
	<para>

	  Right-clicking on any person's box in the Pedigree View will
	  bring up the context menu. Among other useful items, the
	  context menu has submenus listing
	  <guilabel>Spouses</guilabel>, <guilabel>Siblings</guilabel>,
	  <guilabel>Children</guilabel>, and
	  <guilabel>Parents</guilabel> of that person. Insensitive
	  (grayed out) sub-menus indicate the absence of the data in
	  the appropriate category. Similarly to the children menu
	  above, children's and parents' menus distinguish continuing
	  lines from dead ends.

	</para>


<!-- ==== Figure: Pedigree View ==== -->

	<figure id="pedigree-anchor-fig"> 
	  <title>Pedigree View with the Anchor</title> 
	  <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="figures/pedigree-anchor.png" format="PNG" width="500" depth="353" scale="75"/>
              </imageobject>
	      <textobject> 
	        <phrase>Shows Pedigree View with the anchor set.</phrase>
	      </textobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>

<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->
    
        <para>

          An additional advanced scheme of labeling generations exists
          in Pedigree View. It becomes available by setting the anchor
          on some active person. If the anchor is set, the generations
          are labeled as follows.  The anchor person (and his/her
          generation) is labeled as <guilabel>0</guilabel>.  The
          ancestor generations are numbered with positive integers
          (<guilabel>1</guilabel>, <guilabel>2</guilabel>,
          <guilabel>3</guilabel>, etc.) while the descendant
          generations are numbered with negative integers
          (<guilabel>-1</guilabel>, <guilabel>-2</guilabel>,
          <guilabel>-3</guilabel>, etc.). In all cases, the number
          represents the number of generations between the labeled
          generation and the anchor person. In this mode, you can
          travel along the extensive pedigree line and see the number
          of generations counting from the anchor person.

        </para><para>

          To set the anchor, select the <guilabel>Set
          anchor</guilabel> menu item from the right-click context
          menu, when the desired person is the Active person in the
          Pedigree View. The labels will change immediately, and the
          name of the anchor person will appear at the lower left
          corner of the display area.  The set anchor person will stay
          in effect until either the anchor is removed (by selecting
          the <guilabel>Remove anchor</guilabel> item from the context
          menu), or until the active person chosen is unrelated to the
          anchor person. The latter move can be made using extensive
          navigation tools available in &app;, see <xref
          linkend="gramps-nav"/> for the detailed reference.

        </para>

      </sect2>

<!-- ================ Main Window Sub-subsection  -->

      <sect2 id="sources-view">
        <title>Sources View</title>

<!-- ==== Figure: Sources View ==== -->

	<figure id="sources-fig"> 
	  <title>Sources View</title> 
	  <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="figures/sources.png" format="PNG" width="500" depth="353" scale="75"/>
              </imageobject>
	      <textobject> 
	        <phrase>Shows Sources View.</phrase>
	      </textobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>
	<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

	<para>

          The Sources View lists the sources of information stored in
	  the database. This can include various documents (birth,
	  death, and marriage certificates, etc.), books, films,
	  journals, private diaries; virtually anything that can
	  be classified as a source of information. The sources can be
	  used as a reference for any event stored in the
	  database. The Source View lists the
	  <guilabel>Title</guilabel>, <guilabel>ID</guilabel>, and the
	  <guilabel>Author</guilabel> of the source. Any column can be
	  used for sorting the list. The usual rules apply: one click
	  for ascending order, another click for descending order.
	  <guilabel>Column Editor Dialog</guilabel> may be used to
	  rearrange the displayed columns.

        </para>
      </sect2>

<!-- ================ Main Window Sub-subsection  -->

      <sect2 id="places-view">
        <title>Places View</title>

<!-- ==== Figure: Places View ==== -->
  	
          <figure id="places-fig"> 
	    <title>Places View</title> 
	    <screenshot>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="figures/places.png" format="PNG" width="500" depth="353" scale="75"/>
                </imageobject>
	        <textobject> 
	          <phrase>Shows Places View.</phrase>
	        </textobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
          </figure>

<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

	<para>
          The Places View lists the geographical places in which the
	  events of the database took place. These could be places of
	  birth, death, and marriages of people, as well as their
	  home, employment, education addresses, or any other
	  conceivable reference to the geographical location. The
	  Places View lists the places' <guilabel>Name</guilabel>,
	  <guilabel>ID</guilabel>, <guilabel>Church Parish</guilabel>,
	  <guilabel>City</guilabel>, <guilabel>County</guilabel>,
	  <guilabel>State</guilabel>, and
	  <guilabel>Country</guilabel>. All of these columns can be
	  used for sorting by the usual sorting rules.
	  <guilabel>Column Editor Dialog</guilabel> may be used to
	  rearrange the displayed columns.
        </para> 
      </sect2>

<!-- ================ Main Window Sub-subsection  -->

      <sect2 id="media-view">
        <title>Media View</title>

<!-- ==== Figure: Media View ==== -->

	<figure id="media-fig"> 
	  <title>Media View</title> 
	  <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="figures/media.png" format="PNG" width="500" depth="353" scale="75"/>
              </imageobject>
	      <textobject> 
 	        <phrase>Shows Media View.</phrase>
	      </textobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>

<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

	<para>
         
          The Media View is a list of Media Objects used in the
	  database.  Media Objects are any files that relate somehow
	  to the stored genealogical data. Technically, any file can
	  be stored as a Media Object. Most frequently, these are
	  images, audio files, animation files, etc. The list box on
	  the bottom lists the <guilabel>Name</guilabel>,
	  <guilabel>ID</guilabel>, <guilabel>Type</guilabel>, and
	  <guilabel>Path</guilabel> of the Media Object.
	  <guilabel>Column Editor Dialog</guilabel> may be used to
	  rearrange the displayed columns, which obey usual sorting
	  rules. The top part of the GRAMPS window shows a preview (if
	  available) and information about the Media Object.
 
        </para> 
      </sect2>

    </sect1>
  </chapter>
