<chapter id="gramps-mainwin"> 

<!--
	  User Manual for Gramps - a GTK+/GNOME based genealogy program

	  Copyright (C) 2003-2005  Alexander Roitman

	  This document is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify
	  it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by
	  the Free Software Foundation; either version 2 of the License, or
	  (at your option) any later version.

	  This document is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
	  but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
	  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
	  GNU General Public License for more details.

	  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
	  along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software
	  Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
-->

<!-- $Id$ -->

  <title>Main Window</title> 
 
  <para>
    When you open a database (either existing or new), the
    following window is displayed:
  </para>
 
<!-- ==== Figure: Main Window  ==== -->

  <figure id="mainwin-fig" pgwide="1"> 
    <title>GRAMPS Main Window</title> 
    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="figures/mainwin.png" format="PNG" width="500" depth="352" scale="70"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </figure>
	
<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

  <para>
    The main &app; window contains the following elements: 
  </para>

  <variablelist>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Menubar</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The menubar is located at the very top of the window (right
          below the window title) and provides access to all the features
          of &app;.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Toolbar</term>
      <listitem>
        <para> 
          The toolbar is located right below the menubar.  It gives you
	  access to the most frequently used
          functions of &app;. You can set options that control how it
	  appears by going to 
	  <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guisubmenu>Preferences</guisubmenu></menuchoice>. You can also hide it entirely by going to <menuchoice><guimenu>View</guimenu><guisubmenu>Toolbar</guisubmenu></menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Progress Bar</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The Progress Bar is located in the lower left corner of the
	  &app; window. It displays the progress of time consuming
	  operations, such as opening and saving large data bases,
	  importing and exporting to other formats, generating web
	  sites, etc. When you are not doing these types of operations,
	  the Progress Bar is blank.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Status Bar</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The Status Bar is located to the right of the Progress Bar,
          on the very bottom of the &app; window.  It displays
          information about current &app; activity and contextual
          information about the selected items.  The behavior of the
          Status Bar can be adjusted in the Preferences dialog, which
          can be found by selecting
          <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guisubmenu>Preferences</guisubmenu></menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Display area</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The largest area in the center of the &app; window is the
	  display area.  What it displays depends on the currently
	  selected View. We'll discuss Views in detail below.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist> 

<!-- ================ Main Window Subsection  -->

  <sect1 id="gramps-views">
    <title>Views</title>

    <para>Genealogical information is very broad and can be extremely
    detailed. Displaying it poses a challenge that GRAMPS takes on by
    dividing and organizing the information into a series of
    Views. Each View displays a portion of the total information,
    selected according to a particular category. This will become
    clearer as we explore the six different Views, listed
    below:</para>

    <itemizedlist>	
      <listitem><para>People View</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Family View</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Pedigree View</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Sources View</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Places View</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Media View</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Before we launch into a description of each View,
    let's first explain how to switch between Views.</para>

<!-- ================ Main Window Sub-subsection  -->

    <sect2 id="view-modes">
      <title>Switching Views and Viewing Modes</title>

      <para>As mentioned above there are six different Views. In
      addition, there are two different Viewing Modes. You can tell at
      a glance which Viewing Mode you are in: If you see icons listed
      vertically in a sidebar at the left of the window, you are in
      the Sidebar Viewing Mode. If instead you see a series of
      &quot;notebook tabs&quot; (labeled People, Family, Pedigree, Sources,
      Places, Media) that run horizontally across the window, then you
      are in the Tabbed Viewing Mode. You can switch from one Viewing
      Mode to another by selecting <menuchoice><guimenu>View</guimenu><guimenuitem>Sidebar</guimenuitem></menuchoice> from the Sidebar menu item.</para>

      <para>If you're in the Sidebar Viewing Mode, you can select the View 
      you want by clicking one of the sidebar icons.</para>
<!-- ==== Figure: Sidebar Mode ==== -->

      <figure id="side-nofilt-fig"> 
	<title>Sidebar Viewing Mode</title> 
	<screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/mainwin.png" format="PNG" width="500" depth="352" scale="75"/>
            </imageobject>
  	    <textobject> 
	      <phrase>Shows sidebar viewing mode.</phrase>
  	    </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>

 <!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

      <para>If you're in the Tabbed Viewing Mode, you can select the
      View you want by clicking the corresponding notebook tab.</para>

 <!-- ==== Figure: Tabbed Notebook Mode ==== -->
 	  
      <figure id="noside-nofilt-fig"> 
	<title>Tabbed Viewing Mode</title> 
	<screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/noside-nofilt.png" format="PNG" width="500" depth="393" scale="75"/>
            </imageobject>
	    <textobject> 
	      <phrase>Shows tabbed viewing mode.</phrase>
  	    </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>
<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

    </sect2>

<!-- ================ Main Window Sub-subsection  -->

    <sect2 id="people-view">
      <title>People View</title>
      <para>
        When &app; first opens a database, it displays the
	People View (<xref linkend="side-nofilt-fig"/> and <xref
	linkend="noside-nofilt-fig"/>). This view lists
	all the people stored in the database.
      </para>
      <para> 

      You'll note that people are grouped according to their family
      names. To the left of each family name is an arrow. Clicking it
      once will reveal the entire list of people sharing that
      name. Clicking the arrow again will &quot;roll up&quot; the
      list and show only the family name.

      </para>
      <para>

        By default, the People View, displays the following columns:
        <guilabel>Names</guilabel>, &app; <guilabel>ID</guilabel>
        numbers, <guilabel>Gender</guilabel>, and their
        <guilabel>Birth</guilabel> and <guilabel>Death
        dates</guilabel>.  You can add or remove columns to and from
        the display by calling up the <guilabel>Column
        Editor</guilabel> dialog
        (<menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Column
        Editor</guimenuitem></menuchoice>) and checking or unchecking
        the boxes listed. You can also change the position of a column
        in People View by clicking and dragging it to a new position
        in the Editor. Once you have made the changes you want, click
        <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to exit the Editor and see your
        changes in the People View.

      </para>
	
      <note id="columns-tip">
        <title>Column Editor</title>
	<para>
          The Column Editor is available in all Views and works the 
	  same way in each.
        </para> 
      </note>


<!-- ==== Figure: Enabled Filter ==== -->

      <figure id="column-editor-fig"> 
	<title>Column Editor Dialog</title> 
	<screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/column-editor.png" format="PNG" width="444" depth="437"/>
            </imageobject>
	    <textobject> 
	      <phrase>Shows column editor dialog. </phrase>
  	    </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>

<!-- ================ Main Window Sub-sub-subsection  -->

      <sect3 id="filters">
        <title>Filters</title>

	<para>

	Genealogical databases can contain information on many people,
	families, places, and objects. It's therefore possible for a
	View to contain a long list of data that's difficult to
	work with.  &app; gives you a means for controlling this
	condition by allowing you to filter a list to a more
	manageable size.

	</para>

<!-- ==== Figure: Enabled Filter ==== -->

	<figure id="side-filt-fig"> 
  	  <title>Filter Controls Displayed</title> 
	  <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="figures/side-filt.png" format="PNG" width="500" depth="352" scale="75"/>
              </imageobject>
	      <textobject> 
	        <phrase>Shows filter controls.</phrase>
  	      </textobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>

<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

	<para>

	When &app; opens a database, no filtering is in effect. In
	People View, for example, all people in the database are
	listed by default. To filter the list, go to <menuchoice>
	<guimenu>View</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Filter</guimenuitem>
	</menuchoice>. This will place a new menu just above the list
	of People. Click on the double arrows of this menu to get a
	pop-up list of all the criteria by which you can filter the
	People listed. Choose a filter (for example, &quot;Males&quot;
	or &quot;People with children&quot;) and click
	<guibutton>Apply</guibutton>.

        </para>

        <note id="filter-note">
          <title>Displaying the filter</title>
	  <para>

	  To reduce screen clutter, the filter menu is hidden by
	  default. To display it, go to the <menuchoice>
	  <guimenu>View</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Filter</guimenuitem>
	  </menuchoice> menu. Please understand that even if the
	  filter menu is not displayed, filtering may still be in
	  effect. (Thus, we say that filtering is persistent.)  If you
	  are unsure if your list is filtered, bring up the filter
	  menu (by going to <menuchoice> <guimenu>View</guimenu>
	  <guimenuitem>Filter</guimenuitem> </menuchoice>) and check
	  if any filtering is set.
	  </para>
	</note>  

	  
	 <tip id="filt-tip">
           <title>Example filter use</title>
	   <para>
             To show males only, choose the <guilabel>Males</guilabel>
	     filter, then click the <guibutton>Apply</guibutton>
	     button. To cancel any filtering, set the filter to
	     <guilabel>Entire Database</guilabel> and then click the
	     <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> button.
            </para>
	  </tip>
	  
        </sect3>
      </sect2>
      
<!-- ================ Main Window Sub-subsection  -->

      <sect2 id="family-view">
        <title>Family View</title>
	<para>
          The Family View displays the family information of a 
	  selected person that we call the Active person. Specifically,
	  it shows his or her closest relationships.
        </para>
	
<!-- ==== Figure: Family View ==== -->

	<figure id="family-fig"> 
 	  <title>Family View</title> 
	  <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="figures/family.png" format="PNG" width="500" depth="352" scale="75"/>
              </imageobject>
	      <textobject> 
	        <phrase>Shows Family View.</phrase>
	      </textobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>

	<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

	<para>
	The Family View displays the following series of list boxes:
	</para>

        <variablelist>
  	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>Active person</term>
	    <listitem>
	    <para>
	    Shows birth and death data for the individual you have
	    selected. Double-click inside the box to edit the Active
	    person's information. Click on the double arrow to the
	    right and the currently selected Spouse will become the
	    new Active person.
	    </para>
   	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

  	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>Relationship</term>
	    <listitem>
	    <para>
	    Displays birth and death data for the Active person's
	    Spouse(s). 
	    </para>
	    <note id="spouse-info">
	      <title>Terminology</title>
	      <para> 
	      In the Family View, we use the term &quot;spouse&quot;
	      for sake of simplicity. However, please note that
	      &quot;spouse&quot; may in fact be a domestic partner, a
	      partner in a civil union, etc.
  	      </para>
            </note>

	    <para>
	    Double-click a Spouse to edit his or her
	    relationship to the Active person.  Shift-click (that is,
	    hold down the Shift key while you click) a Spouse to edit
	    his or her personal information.  Click the icon to the
	    top right of the Relationship box to add a new person to
	    the database and to create a relationship between this
	    person and the Active person. Click the middle icon to
	    create a relationship between the Active person and
	    another person already stored in the database. Click the
	    minus (-) button to remove the relationship between the
	    currently selected Spouse and the Active person. (Note
	    that this does not remove the Spouse from the database.)
            </para>
   	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

  	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>Active person's parents</term>
	    <listitem>
	    <para>

	    Click the <guibutton>+</guibutton> or
	    <guibutton>-</guibutton> buttons to add or remove parents
	    of the Active person. Click the right arrow button to make
	    the Father the new Active person and the Mother the new
	    Spouse.

	    </para>
	    </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

  	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>Spouse's parents</term>
	    <listitem>
	    <para>
	    This list box functions the same as that of the Active
	    person's parents.
	    </para>
	    </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

  	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>Children</term>
	    <listitem>
	    <para>

	    Displays the children of the Active person and the
	    currently selected Spouse. The list can be ordered however
	    you want by clicking on a column heading.

	    </para><para>

	    Note that in addition to columns for Name, ID, Gender,
	    Birth Date, and Death Date, there is a column labeled
	    Status.1 This column reflects the relationship between the
	    child and his parents (Birth, Adoption, etc.).

	    </para><para>

	    As with the other list boxes, the Children list box has
	    some associated buttons. Click the left arrow button to
	    make the selected Child the Active person. Click the next
	    button down to add a new person to the database and to
	    make this person a Child of the Active person. Click the
	    next button down to select a person from the database and
	    to make this person a Child of the Active person. Click
	    the lowest button to remove the selected Child from the
	    Family (note that this does not remove the Child from the
	    database).
	    </para>

	    <note id="right-click-menu">
	    <title>Right Click Menu</title>
	    <para>
	    Most of the functions described above can also be executed
	    by right-clicking your mouse.
	    </para>
	    </note>
	    </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

        </variablelist>


	<para>

          The layout of the Family View can be switched from the
          &quot;left-to-right&quot; arrangement shown in <xref linkend="family-fig"/> to the
          &quot;top-to-bottom&quot; arrangement shown in <xref linkend="family-alt-fig"/>. This is
          done by going to
          <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem></menuchoice>
          and selecting the <guilabel>Display</guilabel> section of
          the dialog that appears.

        </para>

<!-- ==== Figure: Family View ==== -->

	<figure id="family-alt-fig"> 
	  <title>Alternative Family View</title> 
	  <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="figures/family-alt.png" format="PNG" width="500" depth="352" scale="75"/>
              </imageobject>
	      <textobject> 
	        <phrase>Shows Alternative Family View.</phrase>
  	      </textobject>
            </mediaobject> 
          </screenshot>
        </figure>

<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

      </sect2>

<!-- ================ Main Window Sub-subsection  -->
      <sect2 id="pedigree-view">
        <title>Pedigree View</title>

	<para>

          The Pedigree View displays a family tree of the Active
	  person's ancestors. The Pedigree View shows up to five
	  generations, depending on the size of the window. Each person is
	  indicated by a box labeled with his or her name. Two lines
	  branch from each box. The top one shows the person's father
	  and the bottom one the mother. Solid lines represent birth
	  relations, while dashed lines represent non-birth relations
	  such as adoption, step-parenthood, guardianship, etc.

	</para>

<!-- ==== Figure: Pedigree View ==== -->

	<figure id="pedigree-fig"> 
  	  <title>Pedigree View</title> 
	  <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="figures/pedigree.png" format="PNG" width="500" depth="352" scale="75"/>
              </imageobject>
	      <textobject> 
	        <phrase>Shows Pedigree View.</phrase>
 	      </textobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>

<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

	<para>

	If you move your mouse over a box, it expands to show birth
	and death dates. If you move your mouse over a line, the line
	gets highlighted, indicating an active link. Double-click the
	line to make the corresponding ancestor the Active
	person. 

        </para>
	
<!-- ==== Figure: Pedigree View ==== -->

	<figure id="pedigree-child-cut-fig"> 
	  <title>Children Menu</title> 
	  <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="figures/pedigree-child-cut.png" format="PNG" width="303" depth="195"/>
              </imageobject>
	      <textobject> 
	        <phrase>Shows Children Menu in Pedigree View.</phrase>
 	      </textobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>

<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

	<para>

	To the left of the Active person is a left arrow button. If
	the Active person has children, clicking this button expands a
	list of the Active person's children. Selecting one of the
	children makes that child the pctive Person.

       </para><para>

	The appearance of the children's names in the menu
	differentiates the &quot;dead ends&quot; of the tree from the
	continuing branches. Children who have children themselves
	appear in the menu in the boldface and italic type, while
	children without children (&quot;dead ends&quot;) appear in a
	regular font. If the Active person has only one child, no menu
	will be displayed (since there is only one choice) and the
	child will become the Active person when the arrow button is
	clicked.

       </para><para>

        The right-hand side of the window shows two right arrow
	buttons.  When the top button is clicked, the Father of the
	Active person becomes the Active person. Clicking the bottom
	button makes the Mother of the Active person the Active
	person. 

        </para> 

<!-- ==== Figure: Pedigree View ==== -->

	<figure id="pedigree-siblings-cut-fig"> 
 	  <title>Personal Context Menu</title> 
	  <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="figures/pedigree-siblings-cut.png" format="PNG" width="500" depth="253" scale="75"/>
              </imageobject>
	      <textobject> 
	        <phrase>Shows Context Menu in Pedigree View.</phrase>
 	      </textobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>

<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->
	
	<para>

	Right-clicking on any person's box in the Pedigree View will
	bring up the &quot;context menu&quot;. Among other useful
	items, the context menu has sub-menus listing
	<guilabel>Spouses</guilabel>, <guilabel>Siblings</guilabel>,
	<guilabel>Children</guilabel>, and
	<guilabel>Parents</guilabel> of that
	person. &quot;Greyed-out&quot; sub-menus indicate the absence
	of the data in the appropriate category. Similarly to the
	children menu above, Childrens' and Parents' menus distinguish
	continuing lines from dead ends.

	</para>


<!-- ==== Figure: Pedigree View ==== -->

	<figure id="pedigree-anchor-fig"> 
	  <title>Pedigree View with the Anchor</title> 
	  <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="figures/pedigree-anchor.png" format="PNG" width="500" depth="353" scale="75"/>
              </imageobject>
	      <textobject> 
	        <phrase>Shows Pedigree View with the anchor set.</phrase>
	      </textobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>

<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->
    
        <para>

	Pedigree View gives you an additional, advanced way of
	labeling generations. This feature becomes available by
	setting the &quot;anchor&quot; on a selected person. If the
	anchor is set, the generations are labeled as follows:
	</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	    The Anchor Person (and his/her generation) is labeled as 
	    <guilabel>0</guilabel>.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	    The ancestor generations are numbered with positive integers 
	    (<guilabel>1</guilabel>,<guilabel>2</guilabel>,
	    <guilabel>3</guilabel>,etc.).
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	    The descendant generations are numbered with negative integers
	    (<guilabel>-1</guilabel>,<guilabel>-2</guilabel>,
	    <guilabel>-3</guilabel>, etc.).
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	    In all cases, the number represents the number of
	    generations between the labeled generation and the anchor
	    person. In this mode, you can travel along the extensive
	    pedigree line and see the number of generations removed
	    from the Anchor Person.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<para>

	To set the anchor, select the person you want as the Active
	person (recall that you can do so in the Pedigree View by
	clicking the line that leads to the person from his or her
	child). Then, while in Pedigree View, right click anywhere in
	the main window. A context menu will appear. Select
	<guilabel>Set anchor</guilabel> and you will see the Active
	person indicated as the anchor in the lower left corner.
	This newly established Anchor Person will remain in effect
	until you right-click again and select <guilabel>Remove
	anchor</guilabel> from the context menu or until a new Active
	person is chosen who is unrelated to the Anchor Person.

        </para>

      </sect2>

<!-- ================ Main Window Sub-subsection  -->

      <sect2 id="sources-view">
        <title>Sources View</title>
	  <para>

	  Sources View lists the sources of certain information stored
	  in the database. These can include various documents (birth,
	  death, and marriage certificates, etc.), books, films,
	  journals, private diaries, - nearly anything that can
	  provide genealogical evidence. GRAMPS gives you the option
	  to provide a source for each event you record (births,
	  deaths, marriages, etc.). The Source View lists the
	  <guilabel>Title</guilabel>, <guilabel>ID</guilabel>, and
	  <guilabel>Author</guilabel> of the source, as well as any
	  <guilabel>Publication</guilabel> information that may be
	  associated with it.

	  </para><para>

	  The list of Sources can be sorted in the usual manner, by
	  clicking on a column heading. Clicking once sorts in
	  ascending order, clicking again sorts in descending
	  order. The <guilabel>Column Editor</guilabel> dialog can be
	  used to add, remove and rearrange the displayed columns.

	  </para>

<!-- ==== Figure: Sources View ==== -->

	<figure id="sources-fig"> 
	  <title>Sources View</title> 
	  <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="figures/sources.png" format="PNG" width="500" depth="353" scale="75"/>
              </imageobject>
	      <textobject> 
	        <phrase>Shows Sources View.</phrase>
	      </textobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>
	<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

      </sect2>

<!-- ================ Main Window Sub-subsection  -->

      <sect2 id="places-view">
        <title>Places View</title>
        <para>

	The Places View lists the geographical places in which the
	events of the database took place. These could be places of
	birth, death, and marriages of people, as well as their
	home, employment, education addresses, or any other
	conceivable reference to the geographical location. The
	Places View lists the places' <guilabel>Name</guilabel>,
	<guilabel>ID</guilabel>, <guilabel>Church Parish</guilabel>,
	<guilabel>City</guilabel>, <guilabel>County</guilabel>,
	<guilabel>State</guilabel>, and
	<guilabel>Country</guilabel>. All of these columns can be
	used for sorting by the usual sorting rules. The
	<guilabel>Column Editor</guilabel> dialog may be used to
	add, remove and rearrange the displayed columns.

	</para>


<!-- ==== Figure: Places View ==== -->
  	
        <figure id="places-fig"> 
	  <title>Places View</title> 
	  <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="figures/places.png" format="PNG" width="500" depth="353" scale="75"/>
              </imageobject>
	      <textobject> 
	        <phrase>Shows Places View.</phrase>
	      </textobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>

<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->
      </sect2>

<!-- ================ Main Window Sub-subsection  -->

      <sect2 id="media-view">
        <title>Media View</title>

<!-- ==== Figure: Media View ==== -->

	<figure id="media-fig"> 
	  <title>Media View</title> 
	  <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="figures/media.png" format="PNG" width="500" depth="353" scale="75"/>
              </imageobject>
	      <textobject> 
 	        <phrase>Shows Media View.</phrase>
	      </textobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>

<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

	<para>
         
          The Media View is a list of Media Objects used in the
	  database.  Media Objects are any files that relate somehow
	  to the stored genealogical data. Technically, any file can
	  be stored as a Media Object. Most frequently, these are
	  images, audio files, animation files, etc. The list box on
	  the bottom lists the <guilabel>Name</guilabel>,
	  <guilabel>ID</guilabel>, <guilabel>Type</guilabel>, and
	  <guilabel>Path</guilabel> of the Media Object. The
	  <guilabel>Column Editor</guilabel> dialog may be used to
	  rearrange the displayed columns, which obey usual sorting
	  rules. The top part of the GRAMPS window shows a preview (if
	  available) and information about the Media Object.
 
        </para> 
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>
