<!--
	  User Manual for Gramps - a GTK+/GNOME based genealogy program

	  Copyright (C) 2003-2005  Alexander Roitman

	  This document is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify
	  it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by
	  the Free Software Foundation; either version 2 of the License, or
	  (at your option) any later version.

	  This document is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
	  but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
	  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
	  GNU General Public License for more details.

	  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
	  along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software
	  Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
-->

<!-- $Id$ -->

<chapter id="gramps-usage"> 
    <title>Usage</title> 
    <para>As commonly encountered in everyday life, in
    &app; there is usually more than one way to
    accomplish something. The alternatives to some actions will therefore 
    be listed as appropriate.</para> 

    <!-- ================ Usage Subsection ================================ -->
    <sect1 id="new-db"> 
      <title>Starting a New Database</title> 
      <para>To start a new database, choose <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>New</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. You will then be 
      prompted with the <guilabel>Create GRAMPS database</guilabel> dialog asking 
      to specify the name under which the new database will be stored. 
      The new database will be created in the BSDDB format, with <filename>.grdb</filename>
      as the default extension.</para> 

          <note id="new-db-notdir-note">
               <title>Selecting file</title>
	      <para>
	      Unlike the version 1.0.X of &app;, this version does not require selecting directory
	      for the database. Please select filename, as you would in any other application.
	      </para>
           </note>

    </sect1>

    <!-- ================ Usage Subsection ================================ -->
    <sect1 id="open-db"> 
      <title>Opening a Database</title> 
      <para>To open a database, either choose <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Open</guimenuitem></menuchoice>
      or click the <guibutton>Open</guibutton> button on the Toolbar. 
      The <guilabel>Open database</guilabel> dialog will appear. 
      </para>
      
      <para>
      The filetype filter in the <guilabel>Open database</guilabel> dialog allows
      you to display files of a certain type. If the <guilabel>All files</guilabel>
      filter is selected (the default), all the files will be shown. The type will
      be deteremined by the extension of the selected filename.
      </para>

      <note id="open-db-note"><title>Selecting file</title>
      <para>
	      Unlike the version 1.0.X of &app;, this version does not require selecting directory
	      for the database. Please select filename, as you would in any other application.
	      </para>
      </note>
      
      <para>If you do not have write permissions for the selected database, it will
      be opened in a Read Only mode. In this mode, the data may be viewed, but
      no changes will be made to the database. To indicate this mode, the title of the
      main window will be appended with <guilabel>(Read Only)</guilabel> text.
      </para>

      <note id="open-db-note2"><title>Opening XML and GEDCOM databases</title>
      <para>
      This version allows direct opening and editing of &app; XML and GEDCOM
      databases. Please keep in mind that, unlike using the native grdb format,
      these formats require holding all data in memory. This leads to performance
      and memory consumption problems which grdb was designed to solve.</para>
      
      <para>While direct opening of a &app; XML or GEDCOM file is convenient
      for a small database, it may prove burdensome for large databases.
      If you experience this, please consider creating a new native (grdb) database
      and importing your XML or GEDCOM data into it. This will make accessing
      your data much more efficient and quick.
	      </para>
      </note>

      <warning id="open-db-warn">
               <title>GEDCOM Editing</title>
	      <para>
		Please keep in mind that some information in GEDCOM file may be lost
		during import into &app;. Simply opening and viewing the file will not change it.
		However, if any changes were made and they were not abandoned upon exit,
		exiting &app; will save the data, with the possible data loss.
	      </para>
           </warning>                

      <para>To open a recently opened database, choose <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Open
      Recent</guimenuitem></menuchoice> and select the filename from the list.
      You can also use <menuchoice><guimenu>Actions</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Recent Documents</guimenuitem></menuchoice>
      from the GNOME <guilabel>Actions</guilabel> menu. 
      </para>

    </sect1>

    <!-- ================ Usage Subsection ================================ -->
    <sect1 id="save-db"> 
      <title>Saving a Database</title>

      <para>A consequence of the new database backend is that the changes, once approved
      by the user, are applied immediately. In short, once you click <guibutton>OK</guibutton> 
      in the Person, Family, Source, Place, Media object, or Event editor, all the changes made to 
      this object are recorded in the database. No saving is necessary, or even possible.
      </para>

      <para>Choosing <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Undo</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> allows you to undo the changes you made, one step at a time.</para>
      
      <tip id="save-tip"><title>Reverting the whole session</title>
      <para>If you would like to revert the whole editing session, choose
      <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Abandon changes
      and quit</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. This will be analogous to quitting
      without saving any changes in other applications. 
      </para>
      </tip>
      
      <para>If you would like to save your database under a different name,
      you can do so by choosing <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Save as...</guimenuitem></menuchoice> and specifying
      the name (and, optionally, format) of your new database.
      </para>
      
      <note id="save-as-note"><title>&quot;Save as&quot; continues editing</title>
      <para>If you use the <guilabel>Save as...</guilabel> function, the editing in the
      main window is performed on the newly made copy. If this is not what you want
      to do, please consider using <guilabel>Export...</guilabel> instead.
      </para></note>
      
    </sect1>

    <!-- ================ Usage Subsection ================================ -->
    <sect1 id="import-data"> 
      <title>Importing Data</title> 
      <para>Importing allows you to incorporate the data from other 
      databases into your currently open &app; database. Currently, 
      &app; can import data from the following formats: &app; database (grdb),
      GEDCOM, &app; XML, &app; package, and GeneWeb. All of these are
      available by choosing <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu>
      <guisubmenu>Import</guisubmenu></menuchoice> and
      selecting an appropriate file.</para>
      
      <para>&app; database (grdb), &app; XML, and &app; package are
      all native &app; formats in that there is no information loss resulting
      from reading from and writing into these formats.
      <variablelist>

      <varlistentry><term>&app; database (grdb)</term>
      <listitem><para>
      The native &app; database format is a specific form of Berkeley database (BSDDB)
      with special structure of data tables. This format is binary and architecture-dependent.
      It is very quick and efficient, but not generally portable across computers with
      different binary architecture (e.g. i386 vs alpha).
      </para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry><term>&app; XML</term>
      <listitem><para>
      The &app; XML file was the default format for the previous stable
      version of &app;. Unlike the grdb format, it is architecture
      independent and human-readable. The database may also have references 
      to non-local (external) media objects, therefore it is not guaranteed 
      to be completely portable. The &app; XML database is created by saving 
      (<menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Save
      As...</guimenuitem></menuchoice>) or exporting (<menuchoice>
      <guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Export...</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>) data in that format.
      </para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry><term>&app; package</term>
      <listitem><para>
      The package is a compressed archive containing the &app; XML
      file and all media objects (images, sound files, etc.) that the 
      database refers to. The &app; package is created by exporting
      (<menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>
      Export...</guimenuitem></menuchoice>) data in that format.
      </para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      </variablelist>

      </para>

      <tip id="import-tip"><title>Opening vs importing</title>
      <para>The difference between opening &app; database (in any format) and 
      importing from &app; or GEDCOM database is that importing incorporates all the 
      data into your currently open database, if any. In contrast, opening the database
      will switch from editing your current data to editing another file.</para></tip>
      
      <para>After choosing an import format, you will be prompted with the 
      <guilabel>Import database</guilabel> dialog asking you to specify the
      file name from which to import. 
      </para> 

      <note id="import-note"><title>Selecting file</title>
      <para>
	      Unlike the version 1.0.X of &app;, this version does not require selecting directory
	      for the database. Please select filename, as you would in any other application.
	      </para>
      </note>

      <para>Upon starting the GEDCOM import, &app; 
      will display the following GEDCOM import dialog with the summary of the 
      information about the data. The information is updated as the import
      progresses. </para>

	<!-- ==== Figure: GEDCOM Import ==== -->
	<figure id="gedcom-import-fig"> 
	<title>GEDCOM Import</title> 
	<screenshot><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata 
		fileref="figures/gedcom-import.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	<textobject> 
	<phrase>Shows GEDCOM Import Window. </phrase>
	</textobject></mediaobject></screenshot></figure>
	<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

      <para>Upon starting the &app; database or &app; package import, 
      &app; will display the progress in the 
      progressbar of its main window.</para>

      <para>If a media file is not found during import, the following dialog
      will prompt you for the possible actions:</para>

	<!-- ==== Figure: Missing media window  ==== -->
	<figure id="missing-media-im"> 
	<title>Missing Media dialog</title> 
	<screenshot><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata 
		fileref="figures/missing-media.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	<textobject> 
	<phrase>Shows Missing Media dialog.  </phrase>
	</textobject></mediaobject></screenshot></figure>
	<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

     <itemizedlist>	
     <listitem>
     <para>To remove the object corresponding to the missing file as well as
      all the references to that object from various database records, click the 
      <guibutton>Remove Object</guibutton> button. This will alter your 
      database so that it will be in a consistent state, but all the 
      references to the missing file will be gone. Use this option if the 
      file is irrevocably lost and there is no possibility of ever replacing 
      it. </para>
      </listitem>

     <listitem>
     <para>To keep the reference to the object corresponding to the missing 
     file, click the <guibutton>Keep Reference</guibutton> button. 
     This will leave things as is, i.e. in an inconsistent state.
     You could supply the missing file later, in which case you will have
     to copy it into your database directory. Choose this option if the
     replacement is possible, but not available right now. </para></listitem>

     <listitem>
     <para>To supply the missing file during import, click the 
     <guibutton>Select File</guibutton> button. This will copy the file you
     select in place of the missing file. No references will be altered
     in the database, and it will be in the consistent state. Use this option
     if the replacement is readily available. 
     </para></listitem>

     <listitem>
     <para>To automatically use the selection made in this dialog for 
     all missing media files, check the <guilabel>Use this selection for all 
     missing media files</guilabel> box. This will remember your choice
     and use it for all media files missing during this import, so that no 
     further dialogs will be presented. Use this option if you anticipate 
     many missing files and want to deal with all of them in the same manner.
     </para></listitem>
    
     </itemizedlist>	

    </sect1>  

    <!-- ================ Usage Subsection ================================ -->
    <sect1 id="export-data"> 
      <title>Exporting Data</title> 
      
      <para>Exporting allows you to share any portion of your &app; database 
      with other researchers as well as to make your database completely 
      portable to another computer. Currently, &app; 
      can export data  to the following formats: &app; database (grdb), &app; XML,
      GEDCOM, &app; package, Web Family Tree, and GeneWeb.</para>
      
      <note id="export-note"><title>Export is saving a copy</title>
      <para>Exporting will create another file with the copy of your data.
      The database currently opened in your &app; window is NOT
      the file saved by your export. Future editing of the currently
      opened database will not alter the copy produced by the export.
      </para></note>


      <para>
      To export data, choose <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu>  
      <guimenuitem>Export</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. This will bring up the 
      <guilabel>Export</guilabel> druid. Its pages will guide you through the
      format selection (see <xref linkend="export-druid-fig"/>), file selection,
      and format specific export options (see <xref linkend="gedcom-export-fig"/>).
      After a final confirmation page, the export will be performed according
      to the choices you have made. At any time, you can click the
      <guibutton>Back</guibutton> and revise any selection, and then go
      forward to redo the export.
      </para>

	<!-- ==== Figure: GEDCOM Export ==== -->
	<figure id="export-druid-fig"> 
	<title>Export druid: format selection</title> 
	<screenshot><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata 
		fileref="figures/export-druid.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	<textobject> 
	<phrase>Shows format selection page of an Export druid</phrase>
	</textobject></mediaobject></screenshot></figure>

    <sect2 id="export-gedcom"> 
      <title>GEDCOM export</title> 

      <para> GEDCOM export options allow you to fine tune your export
      (see <xref linkend="gedcom-export-fig"/>).
      Choose the desired <guilabel>Encoding</guilabel> of the exported file. 
      Use the <guilabel>Filter</guilabel>
      pop-up menu to limit the scope of the export according to the stated rule. 
      Use the <guilabel>Target</guilabel> menu to select the desired GEDCOM 
      dialect. Select your copyright statement from the 
      <guilabel>Copyright</guilabel> menu. Check <guilabel>Do not include
      records marked private</guilabel> to disable the output of private
      records. Check <guilabel>Restrict data on living people</guilabel>
      to limit living people's data to family ties. With this option, 
      information concerning birth, death, addresses, various events, 
      etc. will be omitted in the exported GEDCOM file. If this option is selected, 
      you can further choose whether to use the word "Living" as first name, exclude
      notes, and exclude sources for the living people. Check <guilabel>Reference 
      images from path</guilabel> to tell &app; to use the specific path for your 
      images when writing image references in GEDCOM. 
      </para>

	<!-- ==== Figure: GEDCOM Export ==== -->
	<figure id="gedcom-export-fig"> 
	<title>Export druid: GEDCOM options</title> 
	<screenshot><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata 
		fileref="figures/gedcom-export.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	<textobject> 
	<phrase>Shows GEDCOM options page of an Export druid</phrase>
	</textobject></mediaobject></screenshot></figure>
	<!-- ==== End of Export ==== -->
	</sect2>

    <sect2 id="export-gramps-formats"> 
    <title>Export into &app; formats</title>

      <variablelist>
            <varlistentry><term>&app; database (grdb) export</term>
    <listitem><para>Exporting to the native format will simply make a copy
    of your data under another name. It also may be useful if you have
    directly opened XML or GEDCOM file and would like to save it
    as the grdb file.</para></listitem></varlistentry>

            <varlistentry><term>&app; XML database export</term>
      <listitem><para>Exporting into &app; XML format will
      produce a database compatible with the previous versions of &app;.
      As XML is a text-based human-readable format, you may also use it
      to take a look at your data.
      </para></listitem></varlistentry>

            <varlistentry><term>&app; package export</term>
    <listitem><para>Exporting to &app; package will create a gzip-compressed tar 
      archive (also known as tarball) which contains gramps database, all 
      local media objects, and copies of all external media objects. This is a
      useful format for moving your database to another machine or for sharing 
      it with somebody, while retaining all the features provided 
      by &app;.
      </para></listitem></varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term>Export to CD</term>
    <listitem>
          <para>Exporting to CD will prepare you database directory with all its
      contents to be recorded to the CD. This is done through the 
      <guilabel>burn:///</guilabel> location in Nautilus. After exporting to 
      CD, go to the <guilabel>burn:///</guilabel> location by  
      selecting <menuchoice><guimenu>Go</guimenu>  
      <guisubmenu>CD Creator</guisubmenu></menuchoice> in Nautilus menu
      (unless this location is already displayed by &app;). Your 
      database directory will show up. To record it onto the CD, click the CD 
      icon on the Nautilus toolbar, or select <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu> 
      <guisubmenu>Write to CD</guisubmenu></menuchoice> in Nautilus menu.
      </para></listitem></varlistentry>

      </variablelist>

      <para>If a media file is not found during export, the following dialog
      will prompt you for the possible actions:</para>

	<!-- ==== Figure: Missing media window  ==== -->
	<figure id="missing-media-ex"> 
	<title>Missing Media dialog</title> 
	<screenshot><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata 
		fileref="figures/missing-media.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	<textobject> 
	<phrase>Shows Missing Media dialog.  </phrase>
	</textobject></mediaobject></screenshot></figure>
	<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

     <itemizedlist>	
     <listitem>
     <para>To remove the object corresponding to the missing file as well as
      all the references to that object from various database records, click
      the <guibutton>Remove Object</guibutton> button. This will alter your 
      database so that it will be in the consistent state, but all the 
      references to the missing file will be gone. Use this option if the 
      file is irrevocably lost and there is no possibility of ever replacing 
      it. </para>
      </listitem>

     <listitem>
     <para>To keep the reference to the object corresponding to the missing 
     file, click the <guibutton>Keep Reference</guibutton> button. 
     This will leave things as is, i.e. in the inconsistent state.
     You could supply the missing file later, in which case you will have
     to copy it into your database directory. Choose this option if the
     replacement is possible, but not available right now. </para></listitem>

     <listitem>
     <para>To supply the missing file during export, click the 
     <guibutton>Select File</guibutton> button. This will copy the file you
     select in place of the missing file. No references will be altered
     in the database, and it will be in the consistent state. Use this option
     if the replacement is readily available. 
     </para></listitem>
    
     <listitem>
     <para>To automatically use the selection made in this dialog for 
     all missing media files, check the <guilabel>Use this selection for all 
     missing media files</guilabel> box. This will remember your choice
     and use it for all media files missing during this export, so that no 
     further dialogs will be presented. Use this option if you anticipate 
     many missing files and want to deal with all of them in the same manner.
     </para></listitem>

     </itemizedlist>	


      </sect2>

    <sect2 id="export-other-formats"> 
    <title>Export into other formats</title>

      <variablelist>
            <varlistentry><term>Web Family Tree</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>Exporting to Web Family Tree will create the text file suitable 
      as an input for the WFT program. Specific options include filter selecton
      and the ability to restrict data on living people, that is to limit living 
      people's data to family ties.
      </para></listitem></varlistentry>

            <varlistentry><term>GeneWeb</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>Exporting to GeneWeb will save a copy of your data into
      a popular web genealogy format. To find out more about GeneWeb
            and its format, visit <ulink url="http://cristal.inria.fr/~ddr/GeneWeb/en/"
       type="http">this site.</ulink>
      </para></listitem></varlistentry>

            <varlistentry><term>vCalendar and vCard</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>Exporting to vCalendar or vCard will save information in a 
      format used in many calendaring and addressbook applications,
      sometimes called PIM for Personal Information Manager.
      </para></listitem></varlistentry>

      </variablelist>
      </sect2>

    </sect1>

    <!-- ================ Usage Subsection ================================ -->
    <sect1 id="gramps-edit-quick"> 
      <title>Editing Data: Quick Start</title> 
	<para> Editing any portion of data allows you to amend and/or 
	modify information stored in the database. The available editing 
	options include editing personal data, relationship data, data about
	children and parents, and information about sources, places, and media
	objects used in the database. In short, any data stored in the 
	database can be edited! Adding a new piece of information is the process
 	of creating an appropriate empty data structure and subsequently 
	editing that empty structure. </para>
    
    <para>This section refers mainly to the menu items and buttons as the main 
    way of interacting with &app;. In addition to this, &app; provides an 
    extensive set of keybindings. The detailed reference to the keybindings 
    is found in the <xref linkend="append-keybind"/>.
    </para>

      <!-- ================ Usage Sub-subsection ================ -->
      <sect2 id="gramps-add-pers"> 
        <title>To Add a Person</title> 
	<para> To add a person to the database, switch to the People View 
	(<xref linkend="side-nofilt-fig"/>) and then click the 
	<guibutton>Add</guibutton> on the toolbar. 
	Enter any data you know about this person into the <guilabel>Edit 
	Person</guilabel> Dialog (see <xref linkend="edit-pers-fig"/> 
	for details). To edit information about a person already present 
	in the database, select an entry you would like to view/modify, 
	and then click the <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> icon on the toolbar. </para> 
        
        <para>You can also use <guilabel>Add...</guilabel> and 
        <guilabel>Edit...</guilabel> menu items available under 
        the <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>. Or you can right-click on the person
        and select <guilabel>Add...</guilabel> or <guilabel>Edit...</guilabel>
        from the invoked context menu. 
        </para>
      </sect2>

      <!-- ================ Usage Sub-subsection ================ -->
      <sect2 id="gramps-spec-rel"> 
        <title>To Specify a Relationship</title> 
	<para>To specify a relationship, first switch to the Family View 
	(<xref linkend="family-fig"/>). Then click one of the two top buttons on 
        the right of the spouse box. The topmost button adds a new person to the 
        database and to the relationship, while the second top button adds a person 
        that is already in a database to the relationship. </para>

	<para> If using the second button, select the spouse/partner from the list 
        and specify the relationship using the menu at the bottom. If necessary, you 
        can add a person to the list by clicking the <guibutton>+</guibutton> 
        button. &app; will filter the displayed list of people based on the apparent
        relation possibility. Specifically, shown are the people who could possibly
        be in relationship with the active person, as judged by the available birth
        and death information. To override this and display all people from the
        database, check the <guilabel>Show all</guilabel> box. 
	</para>

	<para>
	To edit information about a relationship already present in the database, 
        move the mouse over the <guilabel>Spouse</guilabel> box and double-click. 
        If the relationship lists has more than one person, you can specify the 
        preferred spouse/partner by selecting an appropriate item from the context 
        menu available upon right-clicking into the spouse box. Also, most of the 
        above function are available from the items of this context menu. 
	</para>
      </sect2>

      <!-- ================ Usage Sub-subsection ================ -->
      <sect2 id="gramps-spec-par"> 
        <title>To Specify Parents</title> 
	<para>To specify parents of an active person, first switch to the 
	Family View (<xref linkend="family-fig"/>). Then click the 
	<guibutton>+</guibutton> button on the right of the active person's
	parents list box. Select the parents from two lists and specify the
	parents' relationships to the active person using menus at the bottom. 
	You can also specify parents' relationship to each other. 
	If necessary, you can add a person to the list by clicking the 
	<guibutton>Add...</guibutton> button. </para>
	
	<para> The top and bottom lists contain males and females, 
	respectively. By default, &app; will
	limit both lists to people who could possibly be the parents (judged
	by the date of birth) of the active person. To override this, check
	the <guilabel>Show all</guilabel> box for each list. 
	</para>
	
	<para>To specify parents of the active person's spouse, switch to the 
	Family View and then click the <guibutton>+</guibutton> button on the 
	right of the spouse's parents list box. To edit information about 
	parents already present in the database, move the mouse over 
	the corresponding parents' box and double-click. All these functions can
        also be performed by right-clicking on the parents' box and selecting
        an appropriate item from the context menu. </para>
      </sect2>

      <!-- ================ Usage Sub-subsection ================ -->
      <sect2 id="gramps-spec-ch"> 
        <title>To Specify Children</title> 
	<para>To specify children of an active person, switch to the 
	Family View (<xref linkend="family-fig"/>) and then click either the 
        second or the third button from the top on the right of the children list 
        box. The second button adds a child to the database and to the family, while
        the third button adds a child already present in the database to the family.
	</para>

	<para> If using the third button, select a child from the list and 
	specify	the child's relationship with father and mother using menus 
	at the bottom. If necessary, you can add a person to the list by 
	clicking the <guibutton>Add...</guibutton> button. By default, &app; will
	limit the lists to people who could possibly be the child (judged
	by the date of birth) of the active person. To override this, check
	the <guilabel>Show all</guilabel> box. 
	</para>
        
	<para>
        The relationship of the child to the parents can be modified by selecting 
        an appropriate item from the context menu available upon right-clicking 
        into the children box. Also, most of the above function are available from 
        the items of this context menu.
	</para>
      </sect2>

      <!-- ================ Usage Sub-subsection ================ -->
      <sect2 id="gramps-add-img"> 
        <title>To Add Images</title> 
	<para>You can add images (as well as other media objects) to 
	individual people, events, sources, places, as well as images 
	generally related to the database (e.g. group family photos). </para>
	
	<para> To add images related to a single person, switch to the 
	People View (<xref linkend="side-nofilt-fig"/>), select a person, and 
	then click the <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> icon on the toolbar to 
        invoke the <guilabel>Edit Person</guilabel> Dialog 
	(<xref linkend="edit-pers-fig"/>). Then, select the 
	<guilabel>Gallery</guilabel> tab, and click the 
	<guibutton>+</guibutton> button to invoke 
    the <guilabel>Select a media 
	object</guilabel> dialog. Type the filename or select a file with the 
	image, then provide a title for that image. Keep adding images until you are 
	done. </para>

	<para> To add images related to a relationship (e.g. marriage), 
	switch to the Family View (<xref linkend="family-fig"/>) and then
	double-click on the Spouse box invoke the <guilabel>Marriage/Relationship 
	editor</guilabel> dialog. Select the <guilabel>Gallery</guilabel> 
	tab and click the <guibutton>+</guibutton> button to add 
    an image. </para>

	<para> To add images related to a source or a place, first switch to 
	the Sources View (<xref linkend="sources-fig"/>) or Places 
	View (<xref linkend="places-fig"/>), respectively. Then select the 
	appropriate source or place and then either double-click on it 
	or click the <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> icon on the toolbar to invoke the 
	<guilabel>Source Editor</guilabel> (or <guilabel>Place 
	Editor</guilabel>) dialog. Select the <guilabel>Gallery</guilabel> 
	tab and click the <guibutton>+</guibutton> button to add 
        an image. </para>

	<para> Finally, to add images that are generally related to the 
	database but not limited to any person, relationship, source, or place 
	in particular, switch to the Media View (<xref linkend="media-fig"/>). 
	Then click the <guibutton>Add</guibutton> icon on the toolbar to 
    add an image. 
	If you have already added any images to any individual galleries, 
	you will also find them listed in the Media View. </para>

	<para> In any gallery, you can also use the <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> 
	and <guibutton>-</guibutton> buttons to edit image information
	and to remove the image reference from that gallery. Note that in all
	galleries removing the reference to the image does not remove the image
	from the database. To completely remove the image from the database, 
	delete it from Media View by first selecting it and then 
	clicking the <guibutton>Remove</guibutton> icon on the toolbar. </para>

      </sect2>

      <!-- ================ Usage Sub-subsection ================ -->
      <sect2 id="gramps-edit-src-plc"> 
        <title>To Edit Sources and Places</title> 

	<para> To add a source or a place to the database, switch to 
	the appropriate Sources View (<xref linkend="sources-fig"/>) or 
	Places View (<xref linkend="places-fig"/>). 
	Then click the <guibutton>Add</guibutton> icon on the toolbar to add a
	source/place. Enter the information into the <guilabel>Source 
	Editor</guilabel> (or <guilabel>Place Editor</guilabel>) dialog. 
	</para>

	<para> To edit information about sources and places already present
	in the database, switch to the appropriate view, select an entry
	you would like to view/modify, and then click the 
	<guibutton>Edit</guibutton> icon on the toolbar. Alternatively, you 
        may double-click on the entry to edit it. 
	</para>

      </sect2>
    </sect1>
      
    <!-- ================ Usage Subsection ================================ -->
    <sect1 id="gramps-edit-complete"> 
      <title>Editing Data: Complete Description</title> 
      <para> This section provides a complete description of all editing 
      options for all pieces of data in the &app; database. It refers mainly 
      to the menu items and buttons as the main way of interacting with &app;. 
      In addition to this, &app; provides an extensive set of keybindings. 
      The detailed reference to the keybindings is found in 
      the <xref linkend="append-keybind"/>.</para>

<note id="edit-button-note">
<title>Add, Remove, and Edit buttons</title>
<para>In order to save precious screen space, most of the
<guibutton>Add</guibutton>, <guibutton>Remove</guibutton>,
and <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> buttons no longer are labeled
with text. Instead, the first two use <guibutton>+</guibutton> and
<guibutton>-</guibutton> icons, and the third uses the icon
depicting a pen on top of a paper sheet.</para>

<para>We will continue referring to the latter as the <guibutton>Edit</guibutton>
button, while using <guibutton>+</guibutton> and
<guibutton>-</guibutton> to denote the former two buttons.
</para></note>

      <!-- ================ Usage Sub-subsection ================ -->
      <sect2 id="adv-pers"> 
        <title>Personal Information</title> 
	<para> Editing of personal data can be performed in the 
	following ways: </para>
	<variablelist>
	<varlistentry><term>From the People View:</term><listitem><para> 
	  Double-click the name of the person whose data you would like 
	  to edit, or select the name by single click and then click the 
	  <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> icon on the toolbar. You may also select 
      the name and then press <keycap>Return</keycap>. Finally, you may select 
      <guimenuitem>Edit...</guimenuitem> from the <guisubmenu>Edit</guisubmenu>
      menu of &app; or choose <guimenuitem>Edit</guimenuitem> from the context 
      menu that appears upon right-click on the name.
	  </para></listitem></varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term>From the Family View:</term><listitem><para>
	  To edit active person's data, move the mouse into the
	  <guilabel>Active person</guilabel> box, then double-click,
	  or use any of the menu items described above.
	  To edit Spouse's data, Shift-click desired spouse entry. Also, from
	  <guilabel>Spouse</guilabel> and <guilabel>Children</guilabel> boxes
	  you may select the desired person, right-click, and then select the
	  menu item from the context menu to edit the selected person's data.
	  </para></listitem></varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term>From the Pedigree View:</term><listitem><para>
	  Move the mouse into the box bearing the name of the person whose
	  data you would like to edit, then double-click.
	  </para></listitem></varlistentry>
	  
	</variablelist>
	
	<para> With either method, the following <guilabel>Edit 
	Person</guilabel> dialog will appear: </para>

	<!-- ==== Figure: Edit Person dialog ==== -->
	<figure id="edit-pers-fig"> 
	<title>Edit Person dialog</title> 
	<screenshot><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata 
		fileref="figures/edit-person.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	<textobject> 
	<phrase>Shows Edit Person dialog. </phrase>
	</textobject></mediaobject></screenshot></figure>
	<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->
	
	<para> The top of the window shows the name of the person whose 
	data is being edited. The main part of the window displays ten 
	notebook tabs containing different categories of available 
	information. You can bring any tab to the top for viewing
	or editing by clicking on the appropriate tab heading. 
	The bottom part has <guibutton>OK</guibutton> and
	<guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> buttons. Clicking the 
        <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button 
	at any time will apply all the changes made in all tabs and close the
	dialog window. Clicking the <guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> button at any time will 
	close the window without applying any changes. If any of the data
	in any tab were modified, the alert window will appear with the 
	choices of closing the dialog without saving changes, canceling the
	initial cancel request, or saving the changes. 
	</para>

<note><para>Clicking <guibutton>OK</guibutton> will immediately
save changes to the database (write on disk). Unlike previous versions,
this version of &app; does not have a separate saving function,
all changes are immediate.</para></note>

	<tip><para>
    The tab labels reflect the presence of corresponding information: if the 
    tab contains any data, its label appears boldface; if the tab has no data
    then its label appears regular (not bold). </para></tip>
    
    <para>The tabs provide the following information categories of 
	personal data:
	</para>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>General</guilabel></term>
		<listitem><para> 
	The <guilabel>General</guilabel> tab allows editing of 
	general information about the person. This includes the text 
	entry fields of <guilabel>Given name</guilabel>, 
	<guilabel>Family name</guilabel>, <guilabel>Family prefix</guilabel> 
	(such as de or van), <guilabel>Suffix</guilabel> (e.g. Jr. or III), 
	<guilabel>Title</guilabel> (e.g. Dr. or Rev.), 
	<guilabel>Nickname</guilabel> (Bob for Robert), 
	<guilabel>Type</guilabel> of the name (birth name, married name, etc.)
	and <guilabel>Date</guilabel> and <guilabel>Place</guilabel> of birth 
	and death. Some of these (<guilabel>Family name</guilabel>,
	<guilabel>Type</guilabel>, and both <guilabel>Place</guilabel> fields), 
	also provide autocompletion feature: as you type in these fields, the menu
	is displayed below the field with the available entries from the database
	that are compatible with your partial input. This allows for a quick selection
	of an available entry by selecting in from the menu, either using
	the mouse or arrows and <keycap>Return</keycap> key.
</para>

<para>The <guilabel>Edit</guilabel> button located by the <guilabel>Family name</guilabel>
entry allows editing the preferred name in complete detail, by invoking the <guilabel>Name
Editor</guilabel> dialog (see <xref linkend="adv-an"/>).

</para>
	
	<para>
	The <guilabel>Gender</guilabel> radio buttons offer
	the choice of person's gender between <guilabel>male</guilabel>,
	<guilabel>female</guilabel>, and <guilabel>unknown</guilabel>. 
	Clicking the colored circle buttons (green, yellow, or red, also called LED buttons)
	located next to 
    the birth and death Date fields will bring up the <guilabel>Date Selection</guilabel>
    dialog allowing detailed modification of the date, see <xref linkend="adv-dates"/>.
    Clicking either <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> button located next to 
    the birth and death LED buttons will bring up a dialog allowing you to 
    edit the corresponding event (birth or death) details, see <xref linkend="adv-ev"/>. 
        
	The field <guilabel>ID</guilabel> displays an internal 
	&app; ID number which identifies the user in the
	database. The <guilabel>Image</guilabel> area shows the first
	image available in the <guilabel>Gallery</guilabel> of this 
        person (if any exist).
	</para>
	
	<para>Finally, the <guilabel>Information is complete</guilabel> and
	<guilabel>Information is private</guilabel>  check buttons provides
	the way to mark whether this person's record is complete or 	not and
	whether it is a private record. </para>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
	
	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Names</guilabel></term>
		<listitem>

	<!-- ==== Figure: Edit Person dialog - Names ==== -->
	<figure id="edit-pers-names-fig"> 
	<title>Edit Person dialog - Names</title> 
	<screenshot><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata 
		fileref="figures/edit-person-names.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	<textobject> 
	<phrase>Shows Names Tab of Edit Person dialog. </phrase>
	</textobject></mediaobject></screenshot></figure>
	<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

	<para> The <guilabel>Names</guilabel> tab displays information concerning 
	alternate names of the person and the controls allowing their
	modification. The bottom part displays the list of all alternate names
	of the person stored in the database. The top part shows the details 
	of the currently selected name in the list (if any). The buttons
	<guibutton>+</guibutton>, <guibutton>Edit</guibutton>, 
	and <guibutton>-</guibutton> allow the addition, 
	modification, and removal of an alternate name record from the database. 
	Note that the <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> and 
	<guibutton>-</guibutton> buttons become available only when 
	an alternate name is selected from the list.  
	</para>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
	
	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Events</guilabel></term>
		<listitem>

	<!-- ==== Figure: Edit Person dialog - Events ==== -->
	<figure id="edit-pers-events-fig"> 
	<title>Edit Person dialog - Events</title> 
	<screenshot><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata 
		fileref="figures/edit-person-events.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	<textobject> 
	<phrase>Shows Events Tab of Edit Person dialog. </phrase>
	</textobject></mediaobject></screenshot></figure>
	<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

	<para>The <guilabel>Events</guilabel> tab displays information about 
	the events relevant to the person and controls allowing its
	modification. The bottom part displays the list of all such events 
	stored in the database. The top part shows the details 
	of the currently selected event in the list (if any). The buttons
	<guibutton>+</guibutton>, <guibutton>Edit</guibutton>, 
	and <guibutton>-</guibutton> allow you to correspondingly add, 
	modify, and remove an event record from the database. 
	Note that the <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> and 
	<guibutton>-</guibutton> buttons become available only when 
	an event is selected from the list.  
	</para>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Attributes</guilabel></term>
		<listitem>

	<!-- ==== Figure: Edit Person dialog - Attributes ==== -->
	<figure id="edit-pers-attributes-fig"> 
	<title>Edit Person dialog - Attributes</title> 
	<screenshot><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata 
		fileref="figures/edit-person-attributes.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	<textobject> 
	<phrase>Shows Attributes Tab of Edit Person dialog. </phrase>
	</textobject></mediaobject></screenshot></figure>
	<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

	<para>The <guilabel>Attributes</guilabel> tab displays information about 
	the attributes of the person and controls allowing their
	modification. These could be any personal attributes of a person whose
	description naturally fits into Parameter-Value pairs (e.g. enormous
	generosity can be stored as the parameter "Generosity" with the 
	value "Enormous", etc.). The bottom part displays the list of all  
	attributes stored in the database. The top part shows the details 
	of the currently selected attribute in the list (if any). The buttons
	<guibutton>+</guibutton>, <guibutton>Edit</guibutton>, 
	and <guibutton>-</guibutton> allow you to correspondingly add, 
	modify, and remove an attribute record from the database. 
	Note that the <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> and 
	<guibutton>-</guibutton> buttons become available only when 
	an attribute is selected from the list.  
	</para>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Addresses</guilabel></term>
		<listitem>

	<!-- ==== Figure: Edit Person dialog - Addresses ==== -->
	<figure id="edit-pers-addresses-fig"> 
	<title>Edit Person dialog - Addresses</title> 
	<screenshot><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata 
		fileref="figures/edit-person-addresses.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	<textobject> 
	<phrase>Shows Addresses Tab of Edit Person dialog. </phrase>
	</textobject></mediaobject></screenshot></figure>
	<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

	<para>The <guilabel>Addresses</guilabel> tab displays information about 
	the addresses of the person and the controls allowing their
	modification. The bottom part displays the list of all 
	addresses stored in the database. The top part shows the details 
	of the currently selected address in the list (if any). The buttons
	<guibutton>+</guibutton>, <guibutton>Edit</guibutton>, 
	and <guibutton>-</guibutton> allow you to correspondingly add, 
	modify, and remove an address record from the database. 
	Note that the <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> and 
	<guibutton>-</guibutton> buttons become available only when 
	an address is selected from the list.  
	</para>

        <para>Some reports allow you to restrict data on living people. 
        In particular, that option will omit the addresses of people who 
        are currently alive.</para>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Notes</guilabel></term>
		<listitem>

	<!-- ==== Figure: Edit Person dialog - Notes ==== -->
	<figure id="edit-pers-notes-fig"> 
	<title>Edit Person dialog - Notes</title> 
	<screenshot><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata 
		fileref="figures/edit-person-notes.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	<textobject> 
	<phrase>Shows Notes Tab of Edit Person dialog. </phrase>
	</textobject></mediaobject></screenshot></figure>
	<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

	<para>The <guilabel>Notes</guilabel> tab displays information about 
	the notes concerning the person. These could be any notes which do not
	naturally fit into the Parameter-Value pairs available to Attributes. 
	To add a note or modify existing notes simply edit the text in the 
	text entry field.
    </para>
    
    <para>The <guilabel>Format</guilabel> option allows you to set the 
    appearance of the note in the output (i.e. in reports and web pages). 
    Selecting 
    <guilabel>Flowed</guilabel> will replace all multiple spaces, tabs, 
    and single end-of-line characters with single space in the output. 
    The two consecutive new lines (i.e. an empty line) denote a new paragraph.
    Selecting <guilabel>Preformatted</guilabel> will honor all multiple spaces
    tabs, and new lines, so that the output will appear as it is entered
    into the text entry field. 
	</para>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Sources</guilabel></term>
		<listitem>

	<!-- ==== Figure: Edit Person dialog - Sources ==== -->
	<figure id="edit-pers-sources-fig"> 
	<title>Edit Person dialog - Sources</title> 
	<screenshot><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata 
		fileref="figures/edit-person-sources.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	<textobject> 
	<phrase>Shows Sources Tab of Edit Person dialog. </phrase>
	</textobject></mediaobject></screenshot></figure>
	<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

	<para>The <guilabel>Sources</guilabel> tab displays information about 
	the sources related to the person and controls allowing its modification. 
    These could be any general sources which refer to the person but do not 
    describe specifically any event.
    For example, Aunt Martha's memoirs may mention her great grandson Paul,
    so the researcher may assume that this person (Paul) existed and cite 
    the memoirs as the source for this assumption. 
	</para>
	
	<tip><para>Sources documenting
    specific events are better recorded in relation to those events, under the
    <guilabel>Events</guilabel> tab. The person's <guilabel>Sources</guilabel>
    tab is best used for general source references.</para></tip>
    
    <para>The central part displays the list of all source references stored 
    in the database in relation to the person. The 
    buttons <guibutton>+</guibutton>, 
	<guibutton>Edit</guibutton>, and <guibutton>-</guibutton> 
	allow you to correspondingly add, modify, and remove a source reference  
	to this person. Note that the <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> and 
	<guibutton>-</guibutton> buttons become available only when 
	a source reference is selected from the list. </para>

		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>


	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Gallery</guilabel></term>
		<listitem>

	<!-- ==== Figure: Edit Person dialog - Gallery ==== -->
	<figure id="edit-pers-gallery-fig"> 
	<title>Edit Person dialog - Gallery</title> 
	<screenshot><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata 
		fileref="figures/edit-person-gallery.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	<textobject> 
	<phrase>Shows Gallery Tab of Edit Person dialog. </phrase>
	</textobject></mediaobject></screenshot></figure>
	<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

	<para>The <guilabel>Gallery</guilabel> tab displays information about 
	media objects associated with the person and controls allowing subsequent 
	modification. The central part shows the list of all such media objects. 
	For media object which are valid image files, previews of images are 
	displayed. For other objects such as audio files, movie files, etc., a 
	corresponding file type icon is displayed instead.</para>
	
	<tip><para> The first available
	image in the gallery will be also displayed in the
	<guilabel>Image</guilabel> area in the <guilabel>General</guilabel> 
	tab. </para></tip>

	<para>
	The buttons <guibutton>+</guibutton>,
    <guibutton>Select</guibutton>,
	<guibutton>Edit</guibutton>, and <guibutton>-</guibutton> allow
	you to correspondingly add a new image, add a reference to an image already
    stored in the database, modify, and remove a media object reference 
	to this person. Note that the <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> and 
	<guibutton>-</guibutton> buttons become available only when 
	a media object is selected from the list. 
	</para>

	<note><para>Removing a media object from a person's gallery does not 
        remove it from the database. It only removes the reference to that 
        object from this person's record. 
	</para></note>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Internet</guilabel></term>
		<listitem>

	<!-- ==== Figure: Edit Person dialog - Internet ==== -->
	<figure id="edit-pers-internet-fig"> 
	<title>Edit Person dialog - Internet</title> 
	<screenshot><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata 
		fileref="figures/edit-person-internet.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	<textobject> 
	<phrase>Shows Internet Tab of Edit Person dialog. </phrase>
	</textobject></mediaobject></screenshot></figure>
	<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

	<para>The <guilabel>Internet</guilabel> tab displays information about 
	Internet addresses relevant to the person and the controls
	allowing data modification. The bottom part displays the list of all 
	such Internet addresses stored in the database. The top part shows the
	details of the currently selected addresses in the list (if any). 
	The buttons <guibutton>+</guibutton>, 
	<guibutton>Edit</guibutton>,  and <guibutton>-</guibutton> 
	allow you to correspondingly add, modify, and remove an Internet address 
	record from the database. The button <guibutton>Go</guibutton> allows
	opening a web-page with the corresponding address with your default 
	browser. Note that the <guibutton>Edit</guibutton>, 
	<guibutton>-</guibutton>, and <guibutton>Go</guibutton> buttons 
	become available only when an address is selected from the list.  
	</para>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>LDS</guilabel></term>
		<listitem>

	<!-- ==== Figure: Edit Person dialog - LDS ==== -->
	<figure id="edit-pers-lds-fig"> 
	<title>Edit Person dialog - LDS</title> 
	<screenshot><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata 
		fileref="figures/edit-person-lds.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	<textobject> 
	<phrase>Shows LDS Tab of Edit Person dialog. </phrase>
	</textobject></mediaobject></screenshot></figure>
	<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

	<para>The <guilabel>LDS</guilabel> tab displays information 
	about LDS ordinances of the person and controls allowing 
	modification. These are <guilabel>LDS baptism</guilabel>, 
	<guilabel>Endowment</guilabel>, and <guilabel>Sealed to 
	parents</guilabel> ordinances, as labeled inside the tab. 
	Each ordinance is described by its date, LDS temple, and Place where 
	it happened. An additional pop-up menu <guilabel>Parents</guilabel> is
	available for the <guilabel>Sealed to parents</guilabel> ordinance.
	Each ordinance can further be described by its status through the 
	selections available in the <guilabel>Status</guilabel> pop-up 
	menu and can also be referenced by sources and notes via corresponding 
	<guibutton>Sources...</guibutton> and <guibutton>Note</guibutton>
	buttons. 
	</para>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

      </sect2>

      <!-- ================ Usage Sub-subsection ================ -->
      <sect2 id="adv-dates"> 
        <title>Dates</title> 
	<para> This section describes the details of entering and modifying dates.
	Dates are important in genealogical research, so &app; goes a long
	way to preserve and use any date information available.</para> 

      <sect3 id="adv-dates-led">
      <title>Date types and validity indicators</title>
<para>&app; uses color circles to indicate the validity of the entered date. </para>

<tip><title>Date LED buttons</title>
<para>The color circles are also referred to as the LED buttons.
Clicking on an LED button will invoke the <guilabel>Date selection</guilabel>
dialog described in detail below, see <xref linkend="adv-dates-gui"/> </para></tip>

        <itemizedlist>
        
        <listitem><para> Green circle means that the date is valid and 
        complete regular date (e.g. May 24, 1961). In simple terms, green
        means that the date is uniquely defined up to a day.</para></listitem>

        <listitem><para> Yellow circle means that the date is valid but is
        not a regular date. This could be the date of an alternative type:
        a before date (before May 25, 1962), an after date (after May, 1960),
        an about date (about May 23, 1961), a range (between May 1, 1961 and May 31, 1961),
        or a span (from May 1, 1961 to May 31, 1961). It can also be a complete
        single date, but with quality of Estimated or Calculated. Finally, it could
        be a partial date, i.e. a regular quality single date missing some
        portion, e.g. May 1961 or 1961.</para>
        
        <para>While partial dates do 
        not uniquely define the day, they allow at least for some type of
        comparisons between the dates. </para></listitem>

        <listitem><para> Red circle means that the date is not recognized as 
        a valid date (e.g. "Christmas week of 61", or "the summer when I had surgery"). 
        n that case the date will be stored as a text string. Therefore, no comparison
        with other dates will be available. It is best to avoid such date entries. Same 
        information can be entered as a note for the event of interest instead
        of a date. In the example considered, a better things to do is to
        enter December 1961 as a date and "Christmas week of 61" as a note.
        </para></listitem> 

        </itemizedlist>
        </sect3>

      <sect3 id="adv-dates-parsing">
      <title>Acceptable date entries</title>

	<para>&app; recognizes many 
        formats of exact dates. The numeric formats are determined
        by the default environment &app; is running under. Most European
        countries use DD.MM.YYYY, the US commonly uses MM/DD/YYYY,
        and so on. </para>

<para>Besides exact dates, &app; 
        recognizes many dates that are not regular: before, after, about, ranges
        and spans. It also understands the quality: estimated or calculated.
        Finally, it supports partial dates and many alternative calendars. 
        Below is the list of date entry rules to allow precise date parsing.</para>
        
        <note><title>Date parsing rules</title>
        <para>The list below is only valid for English. If you are using localized version
        of &app;, your version may or may not provide a localized date parser.
        At the time of this writing, localized parsers exist for French, Russian, and
        Spanish languages.</para>
        
        <para>If the localized parser is available for your version, chances are
        that other rules are in effect. If there's no manual in your language yet,
        you may try following your instinct and go with the common ways
        of denoting dates in your language. If all else fails, use the <guilabel>Date
        selection</guilabel> dialog described below.</para></note>

        <itemizedlist>
        
        <listitem><para>Regular single dates can be entered just as you would
        write them in the letter: May 24, 1961 or January 1, 2004.</para></listitem>
        
        <listitem><para> Dates that are not regular should start with the quality:
        estimated or calculated, if applicable. Regular quality does not need to be
        specified, as it is the default. Example: est. 1961, or calc 2005.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem><para> Next should appear the type: before, after, or about.
        Ranges are denoted with "between DATE and DATE" and spans use "from DATE
        to DATE" patterns, where DATE stands for a single date.</para>
        
        <para>Examples: est from 2001 to 2003, before June 1975, est about 2000,
        calc between May 1900 and January 1, 1990.
        </para></listitem>
        
        <listitem><para> Partial dates are entered simply by omitting unknown
        information: May 1961, 2004.</para></listitem>
        
        <listitem><para>
        Alternate calendars are calendars other than Gregorian
        calendar. Currently, &app; supports Hebrew,
        French Republican, Julian, Islamic, and Persian alternate calendars. 
        To specify the calendar other than the default Gregorian,
        append the name of the calendar to the date string, e.g.
        "January 9, 1905 (julian)".
        </para></listitem>

        </itemizedlist>
        </sect3>
        
        <sect3 id="adv-dates-gui"><title>Graphical User Interface for entering dates</title>
        <para>While the above rules provide a quick and easy way for entering most
        common dates, sometimes there is a need to either build a complex date or simply
        check the date using graphical user interface. The <guilabel>Date selection</guilabel>
        dialog can be invoked by clicking the color circle button (also known as the LED
        button) next to the date entry field. </para>
        </sect3>

	<!-- ==== Figure: Date selection dialog ==== -->
	<figure id="adv-dates-gui"> 
	<title>Date selection dialog</title> 
	<screenshot><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata 
		fileref="figures/date-selection.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	<textobject> 
	<phrase>Shows Date selection dialog. </phrase>
	</textobject></mediaobject></screenshot></figure>
	<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

	<para>The <guilabel>Calendar</guilabel> menu allows the choice
	of any supported calendar. The <guilabel>Quality</guilabel> menu
	provides choices of Regular, Estimated, or Calculated quality. The
	<guilabel>Type</guilabel> menu allows to adjust the exact date type:
	Regular, Before, After, About, Range, Span, and Text only.
	A set of controls labeled <guilabel>Date</guilabel> allows setting
	the day, the month, and the year for a date. The second set of controls,
	<guilabel>Second date</guilabel>, is disabled for all dates except
	for those of Range and Span type. For ranges and spans, the
	<guilabel>Second date</guilabel> controls allow setting the details
	of the second date. Finally, the <guilabel>Text comment</guilabel>
	text entry field allows storing an arbitrary text string along with the date.
	</para>
	
	<note><para>If you enter the date outside this dialog, i.e. as a text
	in any date entry field, that text will be copied and stored as the text
	comment string during parsing of entered text.</para>
	
	<para>Therefore, the comment only lives until the next parsing.
	If you have some important text corresponding to the date, you
	are probably better off by saving that text as a Note for the
	corresponding event.</para></note>

      </sect2>

      <!-- ================ Usage Sub-subsection ================ -->
      <sect2 id="adv-rel"> 
        <title>Relationship Data</title> 
	<para> Editing of relationship data is performed in the following 
	<guilabel>Marriage/Relationship Editor</guilabel> dialog which appears 
	after double-clicking on the spouse box in the Family View. Alternatively,
	you may invoke this dialog by right-clicking into the spouse box
	and selecting <guilabel>Edit relationship</guilabel> item from
	the context menu.</para>

 	<!-- ==== Figure: Edit Relationship dialog ==== -->
	<figure id="edit-rel-fig"> 
	<title>Marriage/Relationship Editor dialog</title> 
	<screenshot><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata 
		fileref="figures/edit-rel.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	<textobject> 
	<phrase>Shows Marriage/Relationship Editor dialog. </phrase>
	</textobject></mediaobject></screenshot></figure>
	<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->
	
	<para> The top of the window shows the names of the people whose 
	relationship is being edited. The main part of the window displays 
	seven notebook tabs containing different categories of available 
	information. You can bring any tab to the top for viewing
	or editing by clicking on the appropriate tab heading. 
	The bottom part has <guibutton>OK</guibutton> and
	<guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> buttons. Clicking the 
        <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button 
	at any time will apply all the changes made in all tabs and close the
	dialog window. Clicking the <guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> button at any time will 
	close the window without applying any changes. If any of the data
	in any tab were modified, the alert window will appear with the 
	choices of closing the dialog without saving changes, canceling the
	initial cancel request, or saving the changes. </para> 

<note><para>Clicking <guibutton>OK</guibutton> will immediately
save changes to the database (write on disk). Unlike previous versions,
this version of &app; does not have a separate saving function,
all changes are immediate.</para></note>

	<tip><para>
    The tab labels reflect the presence of corresponding information: if the 
    tab contains any data, its label appears boldface; if the tab has no data
    then its label appears regular (not bold). </para></tip>

	<para>The tabs provide the following information categories of 
	relationship data:
	</para>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>General</guilabel></term>
		<listitem><para> 
	The <guilabel>General</guilabel> tab allows editing of the most general
	information about the relationship: the relationship type. 
	The available types (such as married, partners, etc.) can be chosen 
	from the drop-down <guilabel>Relationship type</guilabel> menu. 
	The <guilabel>ID</guilabel> field displays &app; ID number
	which labels this relationship in the database. The <guilabel>Last
	changed</guilabel> label shows the last modification time for this
	relationship.
	Finally, the <guilabel>Information is complete</guilabel> check
	button provides the way to mark whether this relationship's record is 
	complete or not. </para>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
	
	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Events</guilabel></term>
		<listitem>
	<para>The <guilabel>Events</guilabel> tab displays information about 
	the events relevant to the relationship and the controls allowing 
	modification. The bottom part displays the list of all such events 
	stored in the database. The top part shows the details 
	of the currently selected event in the list (if any). The buttons
	<guibutton>+</guibutton>, <guibutton>Edit</guibutton>, 
	and <guibutton>-</guibutton> allow you to correspondingly add, 
	modify, and remove an event record from the database. 
	Note that the <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> and 
	<guibutton>-</guibutton> buttons become available only when 
	an event is selected from the list.  
	</para>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Attributes</guilabel></term>
		<listitem>
	<para>The <guilabel>Attributes</guilabel> tab displays information about 
	the attributes of the relationship and the controls allowing
	modification. The bottom part displays the list of all such 
	attributes stored in the database. The top part shows the details 
	of the currently selected attribute in the list (if any). The buttons
	<guibutton>+</guibutton>, <guibutton>Edit</guibutton>, 
	and <guibutton>-</guibutton> allow you to correspondingly add, 
	modify, and remove an attribute record from the database. 
	Note that the <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> and 
	<guibutton>-</guibutton> buttons become available only when 
	an attribute is selected from the list.  
	</para>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Notes</guilabel></term>
		<listitem>
	<para>The <guilabel>Notes</guilabel> tab displays information about the 
	notes concerning the relationship. These could be any notes which do 
	not naturally fit into the Parameter-Value pairs available to 
	Attributes. To add a note or modify existing notes simply edit the 
	text in the text entry field.
	</para>

    <para>The <guilabel>Format</guilabel> option allows you to set the 
    appearance of the note in the output (i.e. in reports and web pages). 
    Selecting 
    <guilabel>Flowed</guilabel> will replace all multiple spaces, tabs, 
    and single end-of-line characters with single space in the output. 
    The two consecutive new lines (i.e. an empty line) denote a new paragraph.
    Selecting <guilabel>Preformatted</guilabel> will honor all multiple spaces
    tabs, and new lines, so that the output will appear as it is entered
    into the text entry field. 
	</para>

		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Sources</guilabel></term>
		<listitem>
	<para>The <guilabel>Sources</guilabel> tab displays information about 
	the sources related to the relationship and controls allowing its 
    modification. These could be any general sources which refer to the 
    relationship but do not describe specifically any event.
    For example, Aunt Martha's memoirs may mention that her great grandson Paul 
    was married, so the researcher may assume that this relationship (between 
    Paul and his wife) existed and cite the memoirs as the source for this 
    assumption.
	</para>
	
	<note><para> Sources documenting specific events such as marriages 
    or divorces are better filed in relation to those events, under the 
    <guilabel>Events</guilabel> tab.</para></note>
    
    <para>The central part displays the list of all source references stored 
    in the database for this relationship. The 
    buttons <guibutton>+</guibutton>, 
	<guibutton>Edit</guibutton>, and <guibutton>-</guibutton> 
	allow you to correspondingly add, modify, and remove a source reference  
	to this relationship. Note that the <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> and 
	<guibutton>-</guibutton> buttons become available only when 
	a source reference is selected from the list. </para>

		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Gallery</guilabel></term>
		<listitem>
	<para>The <guilabel>Gallery</guilabel> tab displays information about 
	media objects associated with the relationship and the controls allowing 
	modification of such. The central part shows the list of all such media objects. 
	For media object which are valid image files previews of images are 
	displayed. For other objects such as audio files, movie files, etc., a 
	generic &app; icon is displayed instead. 
    The buttons <guibutton>+</guibutton>,
    <guibutton>Select</guibutton>,
	<guibutton>Edit</guibutton>, and <guibutton>-</guibutton> allow
	you to correspondingly add a new image, add a reference to an image already
    stored in the database, modify, and remove a media object reference 
	to this relationship. 
	Note that the <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> and 
	<guibutton>-</guibutton> buttons become available only when 
	a media object is selected from the list. 
	</para>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>LDS</guilabel></term>
		<listitem>
	<para>The <guilabel>LDS</guilabel> tab displays information 
	about the LDS <guilabel>Sealed to spouse</guilabel> ordinance
	  of the person and the controls allowing 
	modification. The data can include date, LDS temple, and Place where 
	it happened. The ordinance can further be described by its status 
	through the selections available in the <guilabel>Status</guilabel> 
	pop-up menu and can also be referenced by sources and notes via 
	corresponding <guibutton>Sources...</guibutton> and 
	<guibutton>Note</guibutton> buttons. </para>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

     </sect2>

      <!-- ================ Usage Sub-subsection ================ -->
      <sect2 id="adv-src"> 
        <title>Source Data</title> 
	<para> To edit source data, switch to the Sources View and select the
	desired entry in the list of sources. Double-click on that entry or
	click the <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> icon on the toolbar to invoke the 
	following <guilabel>Source Editor</guilabel> dialog: </para>

 	<!-- ==== Figure: Source Editor dialog ==== -->
	<figure id="edit-src-fig"> 
	<title>Source Editor dialog</title> 
	<screenshot><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata 
		fileref="figures/edit-src.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	<textobject> 
	<phrase>Shows Source Editor dialog. </phrase>
	</textobject></mediaobject></screenshot></figure>
	<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->
	
	<para> The top of the window shows the <guilabel>Source
	Editor</guilabel> 
	title of the dialog. The main part of the window displays four notebook 
	tabs containing different categories of available information. You can 
	bring any tab to the top for viewing or editing by clicking on the 
	appropriate tab heading. 
	The bottom part has <guibutton>OK</guibutton> 
	and <guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> buttons. Clicking the 
	<guibutton>OK</guibutton> button at any time will apply all the changes made 
	in all tabs and close the dialog window. Clicking the 
	<guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> button at any time will close the window without 
	applying any changes. </para> 

<note><para>Clicking <guibutton>OK</guibutton> will immediately
save changes to the database (write on disk). Unlike previous versions,
this version of &app; does not have a separate saving function,
all changes are immediate.</para></note>

	<tip><para>
    The tab labels reflect the presence of corresponding information: if the 
    tab contains any data, its label appears boldface; if the tab has no data
    then its label appears regular (not bold). </para></tip>
	
	<para>
	The tabs provide the following information categories of 
	source data:</para>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>General</guilabel></term>
		<listitem><para>The  
	<guilabel>General</guilabel> tab allows editing of the most general
	information about the source: its title, author, abbreviated title, 
    and publication	information. 
    This information can be typed in the appropriate text entry fields. 
	</para>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Note</guilabel></term>
		<listitem>
	<para>The <guilabel>Note</guilabel> tab displays any notes concerning 
	the source. To add a note or modify existing notes simply edit the 
	text in the text entry field.
	</para>

    <para>The <guilabel>Format</guilabel> option allows you to set the 
    appearance of the note in the output (i.e. in reports and web pages). 
    Selecting 
    <guilabel>Flowed</guilabel> will replace all multiple spaces, tabs, 
    and single end-of-line characters with single space in the output. 
    The two consecutive new lines (i.e. an empty line) denote a new paragraph.
    Selecting <guilabel>Preformatted</guilabel> will honor all multiple spaces
    tabs, and new lines, so that the output will appear as it is entered
    into the text entry field. 
	</para>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Data</guilabel></term>
		<listitem>
	<para>The <guilabel>Data</guilabel> tab displays Key/Value
	pairs that may be associated with the source. These are similar
	to the attributes used for other record types. The difference
	from these Key/Value paris and the attributes is that the attributes
	may have source references and notes, while the Key/Value
	data may not.</para>

	<para> The central part shows the list of all Key/Value pairs, if any.
	The buttons <guibutton>+</guibutton> and <guibutton>-</guibutton>
	allow you to correspondingly add and remove pairs. To modify the
	text of Key or Value, first select the desired entry (may be an
	empty entry when new pair has just been added). Then click into
	either Key or Value cell inside that entry and edit the text in place.
	When you are done, click outside the cell to exit editing mode.
	</para>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>


	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Gallery</guilabel></term>
		<listitem>
	<para>The <guilabel>Gallery</guilabel> tab displays information about 
	media objects associated with the given source and controls 
	allowing its modification. The central part shows the list of all 
	such media objects. For media object which are valid image files 
	previews of images are displayed. For other objects such as audio 
	files, movie files, etc., a generic &app; icon is displayed instead. 
    The buttons <guibutton>+</guibutton>,
    <guibutton>Select</guibutton>,
	<guibutton>Edit</guibutton>, and <guibutton>-</guibutton> allow
	you to correspondingly add a new image, add a reference to an image already
    stored in the database, modify, and remove a media object reference 
	to this source.
    Note that the <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> and 
	<guibutton>-</guibutton> buttons become available only when 
	a media object is selected from the list. 
	</para>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>References</guilabel></term>
		<listitem>
	<para>The <guilabel>References</guilabel> tab displays information about 
	database records that refer to this source. If the source is not 
	referenced from any database record, the tab shows an empty list. 
	If the source is referenced from many records, the tab will list 
	all of them. The list can be ordered by any of its column headers:
	<guilabel>Type</guilabel>, <guilabel>ID</guilabel>, or
	<guilabel>Name</guilabel>. Double-clicking on the list entry
	opens up an editor for a corresponding record allowing
	to view or modify the record.</para>
	
	<note><para>Only primary objects can be shown in the 
	<guilabel>References</guilabel> tab: Person, Family, Event, Place, or Media
	object. The secondary objects such as Names and Attributes, although
	may refer the source, will only show up through their primary
	objects they belong to.
	</para></note>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

      </sect2>


      <!-- ================ Usage Sub-subsection ================ -->
      <sect2 id="adv-plc"> 
        <title>Place Data</title> 
	<para> To edit place data, switch to the Places View and select the
	desired entry in the list of places. Double-click on that entry or
	click the <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> icon on the toolbar to invoke the 
	following <guilabel>Place Editor</guilabel> dialog: </para>

	<!-- ==== Figure: Place Editor dialog ==== -->
	<figure id="edit-plc-fig"> 
	<title>Place Editor dialog</title> 
	<screenshot><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata 
		fileref="figures/edit-plc.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	<textobject> 
	<phrase>Shows Place Editor dialog. </phrase>
	</textobject></mediaobject></screenshot></figure>
	<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

	<para> The top of the window shows the <guilabel>Place Editor</guilabel> 
	title of the dialog. The main part of the window displays seven 
	notebook tabs containing different categories of available information. 
	You can bring any tab to the top for viewing or editing by clicking on 
	the appropriate tab heading. 
	The bottom part has 
	<guibutton>OK</guibutton> and <guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> buttons. 
	Clicking the <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button at any time will apply all the 
	changes made in all tabs and close the dialog window. Clicking the 
	<guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> button at any time will close the window without 
	applying any changes. </para> 

<note><para>Clicking <guibutton>OK</guibutton> will immediately
save changes to the database (write on disk). Unlike previous versions,
this version of &app; does not have a separate saving function,
all changes are immediate.</para></note>
	
	<tip><para>
    The tab labels reflect the presence of corresponding information: if the 
    tab contains any data, its label appears boldface; if the tab has no data
    then its label appears regular (not bold). </para></tip>
    

	<para>The tabs provide the following information categories of 
	place data:</para>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>General</guilabel></term>
		<listitem><para>The  
	<guilabel>General</guilabel> tab allows editing of the most general
	information about the place: the title which labels it in the database, 
	city, church parish, county, state, country, longitude, and latitude. 
	This information can be typed in the appropriate text entry fields. 
	</para>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Other names</guilabel></term>
		<listitem><para> 
	The <guilabel>Other names</guilabel> tab displays information concerning 
	other names by which the place might be known and the controls 
	allowing their modification. The bottom part displays the list of all 
	other names of the place stored in the database. The top part shows 
	the details of the currently selected name in the list (if any). 
	The buttons <guibutton>+</guibutton>, 
	<guibutton>Edit</guibutton>, and <guibutton>-</guibutton> allow 
	you to correspondingly add, modify, and remove a name record 
	from the database. Note that the <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> and 
	<guibutton>-</guibutton> buttons become available only when 
	a name is selected from the list. </para>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Note</guilabel></term>
		<listitem>
	<para>The <guilabel>Note</guilabel> tab displays any notes concerning 
	the place. To add a note or modify existing notes simply edit the 
	text in the text entry field.
	</para>

    <para>The <guilabel>Format</guilabel> option allows you to set the 
    appearance of the note in the output (i.e. in reports and web pages). 
    Selecting 
    <guilabel>Flowed</guilabel> will replace all multiple spaces, tabs, 
    and single end-of-line characters with single space in the output. 
    The two consecutive new lines (i.e. an empty line) denote a new paragraph.
    Selecting <guilabel>Preformatted</guilabel> will honor all multiple spaces
    tabs, and new lines, so that the output will appear as it is entered
    into the text entry field. 
	</para>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Sources</guilabel></term>
		<listitem><para> 
	The <guilabel>Sources</guilabel> tab displays information about sources 
	relevant to this place and controls allowing its modification. 
	The central part displays the list of all such source references 
	stored in the database. The buttons <guibutton>+</guibutton>, 
	<guibutton>Edit</guibutton>, and <guibutton>-</guibutton> allow 
	you to correspondingly add, modify, and remove a source reference  
	to this place. Note that the <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> and 
	<guibutton>-</guibutton> buttons become available only when 
	a source reference is selected from the list. </para>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Gallery</guilabel></term>
		<listitem>
	<para>The <guilabel>Gallery</guilabel> tab displays information about 
	media objects associated with the given place and the controls 
	allowing its modification. The central part shows the list of all 
	such media objects. For media objects which are valid image files 
	previews of images are displayed. For other objects such as audio 
	files, movie files, etc., a generic &app; icon is displayed instead. 
    The buttons <guibutton>+</guibutton>,
    <guibutton>Select</guibutton>, <guibutton>Edit.</guibutton>, 
    and <guibutton>-</guibutton> allow
	you to correspondingly add a new image, add a reference to an image already
    stored in the database, modify, and remove a media object reference 
	to this place. 
    Note that the <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> and 
	<guibutton>-</guibutton> buttons become available only when 
	a media object is selected from the list. 
	</para>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Internet</guilabel></term>
		<listitem>
	<para>The <guilabel>Internet</guilabel> tab displays information about 
	Internet addresses relevant to the place and controls
	allowing its modification. The bottom part displays the list of all 
	such Internet addresses stored in the database. The top part shows the
	details of the currently selected addresses in the list (if any). 
	The buttons <guibutton>+</guibutton>,
	<guibutton>Edit</guibutton>,  and <guibutton>-</guibutton> 
	allow you to correspondingly add, modify, and remove an Internet address 
	record from the database. The button <guibutton>Go</guibutton> allows
	you to open a web-page with the corresponding address with your default 
	browser. Note that the <guibutton>Edit</guibutton>, 
	<guibutton>-</guibutton>, and <guibutton>Go</guibutton> buttons 
	become available only when an address is selected from the list.
	</para>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>References</guilabel></term>
		<listitem>
	<para>The <guilabel>References</guilabel> tab displays information about 
	database records (events or LDS ordinances) that refer to this place. If the place is not 
	referenced from any database record, the tab shows an empty list. 
	If the place is referenced from many records, the tab will list 
	all of them. This information cannot be modified from 
	the <guilabel>Place Editor</guilabel> dialog. Instead, the
	corresponding database record (e.g. birth event) has to be brought
	up and its place reference edited. </para>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

      </sect2>

      <!-- ================ Usage Sub-subsection ================ -->
      <sect2 id="adv-media"> 
        <title>Media Data</title> 
	<para> To edit media data, switch to the Media View and select the
	desired entry in the list of sources. Double-click on that entry or
	click <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> on the toolbar to invoke the 
	following <guilabel>Media Properties Editor</guilabel> dialog: </para>

 	<!-- ==== Figure: Edit Media Properties dialog ==== -->
	<figure id="edit-media-fig"> 
	<title>Media Properties Editor dialog</title> 
	<screenshot><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata 
		fileref="figures/edit-media.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	<textobject> 
	<phrase>Shows Media Properties Editor dialog. </phrase>
	</textobject></mediaobject></screenshot></figure>
	<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->
	
	<para> The top of the window shows the dialog title. Below the title  
	is the preview of an object and the summary of its properties (ID, 
	path, and object type). The central part of the window displays four 
	notebook tabs containing different categories of available information. 
	You can bring any tab to the top for viewing or editing by clicking on 
	the appropriate tab heading. The bottom part has 
	<guibutton>OK</guibutton> and <guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> buttons. 
	Clicking the <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button at any time will apply all the 
	changes made in all tabs and close the dialog window. Clicking the 
	<guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> button at any time will close the window without 
	applying any changes. </para> 

<note><para>Clicking <guibutton>OK</guibutton> will immediately
save changes to the database (write on disk). Unlike previous versions,
this version of &app; does not have a separate saving function,
all changes are immediate.</para></note>
	
	<tip><para>
    The tab labels reflect the presence of corresponding information: if the 
    tab contains any data, its label appears boldface; if the tab has no data
    then its label appears regular (not bold). </para></tip>
    
	<para>
	The tabs provide the following information categories of 
	media object data:
	</para>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>General</guilabel></term>
		<listitem><para>The  
	<guilabel>General</guilabel> tab allows editing the title which labels 
	this object in the database. The title can be typed in the appropriate 
	text entry field. The <guilabel>Date</guilabel> field allows entering
	the date by typing, while the LED button beside it will invoke a 
	<guilabel>Date selection</guilabel> dialog for setting the date
	graphically.</para>
	
	<note><para>&app; no longer has a concept of local media objects.
	Every media object is referred to by its path. The users are responsible
	for keeping track of the object files. &app; will only reference
	and display the contents, not manage the files themselves.</para></note>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Attributes</guilabel></term>
		<listitem>
	<para>The <guilabel>Attributes</guilabel> tab displays information about 
	the attributes of the media object and controls allowing its
	modification. The bottom part displays the list of all such 
	attributes stored in the database. The top part shows the details 
	of the currently selected attribute in the list (if any). The buttons
	<guibutton>+</guibutton>, <guibutton>Edit</guibutton>, 
	and <guibutton>-</guibutton> allow you to correspondingly add, 
	modify, and remove an attribute record from the database. 
	Note that the <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> and 
	<guibutton>-</guibutton> buttons become available only when 
	an attribute is selected from the list. </para>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Notes</guilabel></term>
		<listitem>
	<para>The <guilabel>Notes</guilabel> tab displays information about the 
	notes concerning the media object. These could be any notes which do 
	not naturally fit into the Parameter-Value pairs available to 
	Attributes. To add a note or modify existing notes simply edit the 
	text in the text entry field. </para>

    <para>The <guilabel>Format</guilabel> option allows you to set the 
    appearance of the note in the output (i.e. in reports and web pages). 
    Selecting 
    <guilabel>Flowed</guilabel> will replace all multiple spaces, tabs, 
    and single end-of-line characters with single space in the output. 
    The two consecutive new lines (i.e. an empty line) denote a new paragraph.
    Selecting <guilabel>Preformatted</guilabel> will honor all multiple spaces
    tabs, and new lines, so that the output will appear as it is entered
    into the text entry field. 
	</para>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>References</guilabel></term>
		<listitem>
	<para>The <guilabel>References</guilabel> tab displays information about 
	database records that refer to this media object. If the object is not 
	referenced from any database record, the tab shows an empty list. 
	If the object is referenced from many records, the tab will list 
	all of them. The list can be ordered by any of its column headers:
	<guilabel>Type</guilabel>, <guilabel>ID</guilabel>, or
	<guilabel>Name</guilabel>. Double-clicking on the list entry
	opens up an editor for a corresponding record allowing
	to view or modify the record.</para>
	
	<note><para>Only primary objects can be shown in the 
	<guilabel>References</guilabel> tab: Person, Family, Event, Source, or Place.
	The secondary objects such as Names and Attributes, although
	able to refer the media object, will only show up through their primary
	objects they belong to.
	</para></note>
			</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

      </sect2>

      <!-- ================ Usage Sub-subsection ================ -->
      <sect2 id="adv-ev"> 
        <title>Events</title> 
	<para> Events are edited through the following <guilabel>Event
	Editor</guilabel> dialog: </para> 

 	<!-- ==== Figure: Event Editor dialog ==== -->
	<figure id="edit-ev-fig"> 
	<title>Event Editor dialog</title> 
	<screenshot><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata 
		fileref="figures/edit-ev.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	<textobject> 
	<phrase>Shows Event Editor dialog. </phrase>
	</textobject></mediaobject></screenshot></figure>
	<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

	<para> The top of the window shows the dialog title including the name
	of the persons whose event is being edited. The central part of the 
	window displays four notebook tabs containing different categories of 
	available information. You can bring any tab to the top for viewing or 
	editing by clicking on the appropriate tab heading. The bottom part has 
	<guibutton>OK</guibutton> and <guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> buttons. 
	Clicking the <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button at any time will apply all the 
	changes made in all tabs and close the dialog window. Clicking the 
	<guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> button at any time will close the window without 
	applying any changes. </para> 
	
	<tip><para>
    The tab labels reflect the presence of corresponding information: if the 
    tab contains any data, its label appears boldface; if the tab has no data
    then its label appears regular (not bold). </para></tip>

	<para>
    The tabs provide the following information categories of 
	the event data: </para>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>General</guilabel></term>
		<listitem><para>The  
	<guilabel>General</guilabel> tab allows editing of the most general
	information about the event: its type, date, place, cause, and
	description. The type can be selected from available types listed 
	in the <guilabel>Event type </guilabel> drop-down menu. The rest 
	of the information can be typed in the appropriate text entry fields. 
	Check the <guilabel>Private record</guilabel> box to mark this event
	record as private. This will give you a chance to omit this event from
	being included in reports, if you choose so among the report 
	generation options. </para>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Sources</guilabel></term>
		<listitem><para>The  
	<guilabel>Sources</guilabel> tab displays information about sources 
	relevant to this event and controls allowing its modification. 
	The central part displays the list of all such sources references 
	stored in the database. The buttons <guibutton>+</guibutton>, 
	<guibutton>Edit</guibutton>, and <guibutton>-</guibutton> 
	allow you to correspondingly add, modify, and remove a source reference  
	to this event. Note that the <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> and 
	<guibutton>-</guibutton> buttons become available only when 
	a source reference is selected from the list. </para>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Note</guilabel></term>
		<listitem>
	<para>The <guilabel>Note</guilabel> tab displays any notes concerning 
	the event. To add a note or modify existing notes simply edit the 
	text in the text entry field.
	</para>

    <para>The <guilabel>Format</guilabel> option allows you to set the 
    appearance of the note in the output (i.e. in reports and web pages). 
    Selecting 
    <guilabel>Flowed</guilabel> will replace all multiple spaces, tabs, 
    and single end-of-line characters with single space in the output. 
    The two consecutive new lines (i.e. an empty line) denote a new paragraph.
    Selecting <guilabel>Preformatted</guilabel> will honor all multiple spaces
    tabs, and new lines, so that the output will appear as it is entered
    into the text entry field. 
	</para>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Witnesses</guilabel></term>
		<listitem><para>The 
	<guilabel>Witnesses</guilabel> tab displays information about witnesses 
	relevant to this event and controls allowing its modification. 
	The central part displays the list of all such witnesses 
	stored in the database. The buttons <guibutton>+</guibutton>, 
	<guibutton>Edit</guibutton>, and <guibutton>-</guibutton> 
	allow you to correspondingly add, modify, and remove a witness reference  
	to this event, see <xref linkend="adv-wit"/>. Note that the <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> and 
	<guibutton>-</guibutton> buttons become available only when 
	a witness reference is selected from the list. </para>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

      </sect2>

      <!-- ================ Usage Sub-subsection ================ -->
      <sect2 id="adv-si"> 
        <title>Source Information</title> 
	<para> When adding source references to events, places, etc., 
	the following dialog appears: </para>

 	<!-- ==== Figure: Source Information dialog ==== -->
	<figure id="edit-si-fig"> 
	<title>Source Information dialog</title> 
	<screenshot><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata 
		fileref="figures/edit-si.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	<textobject> 
	<phrase>Shows Source Information dialog. </phrase>
	</textobject></mediaobject></screenshot></figure>
	<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

	<para> The top of the window shows the dialog title. The central part 
	displays the source information. The bottom part has 
	<guibutton>OK</guibutton> and <guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> buttons.  
	Clicking the <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button at any time will apply all the 
	changes made and close the dialog window. Clicking the 
	<guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> button at any time will close the window without 
	applying any changes. </para> 

	<para> The source can be selected from available sources listed in the
	<guilabel>Title</guilabel> drop-down menu. If the source you are
	referencing is not present in the database yet, you can enter it into
	the database. To do this, click the <guibutton>New...</guibutton> button 
	and enter source information into the invoked <guilabel>Source 
	Editor</guilabel> dialog. You can also set the details specific for 
	this particular reference: confidence, volume/file/page, date, text, 
	and comments. Choose the confidence 
	level from the <guilabel>Confidence</guilabel> drop-down menu. 
	The rest of the details can be typed in the appropriate text entry
	fields. </para>
	
	<tip><para>Information in this dialog is specific to the particular reference.
	A single source can be referenced many times, and all such references will
	have in common the overall source information. This dialog lets you provide
	reference-specific data, such as relevant quotes, comments, confidence,
	page numbers, etc, to further specify and document the reference.</para></tip>

      </sect2>
      
      <!-- ================ Usage Sub-subsection ================ -->
      <sect2 id="adv-an"> 
        <title>Names</title> 
	<para> Names are edited through the following 
	<guilabel>Name Editor</guilabel> dialog: </para>

 	<!-- ==== Figure: Names Editor dialog ==== -->
	<figure id="edit-an-fig"> 
	<title>Name Editor dialog</title> 
	<screenshot><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata 
		fileref="figures/edit-an.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	<textobject> 
	<phrase>Shows Name Editor dialog. </phrase>
	</textobject></mediaobject></screenshot></figure>
	<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->
	
	<para> The top of the window shows the dialog title including the name
	of the person whose name is being edited. The central part 
	of the window displays three notebook tabs containing different 
	categories of available information. You can bring any tab to the 
	top for viewing or editing by clicking on the appropriate tab heading. 
	The bottom part has <guibutton>OK</guibutton> and 
	<guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> buttons. Clicking the 
	<guibutton>OK</guibutton> button at any time will apply all the 
	changes made in all tabs and close the dialog window. Clicking the 
	<guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> button at any time will close the window without 
	applying any changes. </para> 
	
	<tip><para>
    The tab labels reflect the presence of corresponding information: if the 
    tab contains any data, its label appears boldface; if the tab has no data
    then its label appears regular (not bold). </para></tip>
    
    
    <para>The tabs provide the following information categories of 
	the alternate name data: </para>

 	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>General</guilabel></term>
		<listitem><para>The 
	<guilabel>General</guilabel> tab allows editing of general
	information about the alternate name: given name, family name, 
	patronymic, family 
	prefix, suffix, title, and type of the name. The information can be 
	typed in the appropriate text entry fields. The family name and the 
	type can be also selected from available choices listed in the 
	appropriate drop-down menus. </para>
	
	<para><guilabel>Options</guilabel> allow you to adjust specific
	grouping, sorting, and displaying properties of this name, as well
	as to provide the date corresponding to the name. The 
	<guilabel>Grouping</guilabel> field provides an alternative
	grouping node for a given name, overriding the default grouping
	based on the family name. This may be necessary with similar
	family names that need to be grouped together. To enable
	typing into this field, check the <guilabel>Override</guilabel>
	check button. The <guilabel>Sort as</guilabel> and 
	<guilabel>Display as</guilabel> determine the manner
	in which the name appears in the People View and in the reports.
	The <guilabel>Date</guilabel> can provide information on
	the validity of this name -- use spans as necessary.
	Check the <guilabel>Private record</guilabel> box to mark this name
	record as private. This will give you a chance to omit this name from
	being included in reports, if you choose so among the report 
	generation options. </para>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Sources</guilabel></term>
		<listitem><para>The 
	<guilabel>Sources</guilabel> tab displays information about sources 
	relevant to this name and controls allowing its modification. 
	The central part displays the list of all such sources' references 
	stored in the database. The buttons <guibutton>+</guibutton>, 
	<guibutton>Edit</guibutton>, and <guibutton>-</guibutton> 
	allow you to correspondingly add, modify, and remove a source reference  
	to this name. Note that the <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> and 
	<guibutton>-</guibutton> buttons become available only when 
	a source reference is selected from the list. </para>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Note</guilabel></term>
		<listitem>
	<para>The <guilabel>Note</guilabel> tab displays any notes concerning 
	the name. To add a note or modify existing notes simply edit the 
	text in the text entry field.
	</para>

    <para>The <guilabel>Format</guilabel> option allows you to set the 
    appearance of the note in the output (i.e. in reports and web pages). 
    Selecting 
    <guilabel>Flowed</guilabel> will replace all multiple spaces, tabs, 
    and single end-of-line characters with single space in the output. 
    The two consecutive new lines (i.e. an empty line) denote a new paragraph.
    Selecting <guilabel>Preformatted</guilabel> will honor all multiple spaces
    tabs, and new lines, so that the output will appear as it is entered
    into the text entry field. 
	</para>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

     </sect2>
      
      <!-- ================ Usage Sub-subsection ================ -->
      <sect2 id="adv-at"> 
        <title>Attributes</title> 
	<para> Attributes are edited through the following 
	<guilabel>Attribute Editor</guilabel> dialog: </para>

 	<!-- ==== Figure: Attribute Editor dialog ==== -->
	<figure id="edit-at-fig"> 
	<title>Attribute Editor dialog</title> 
	<screenshot><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata 
		fileref="figures/edit-at.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	<textobject> 
	<phrase>Shows Attribute Editor dialog. </phrase>
	</textobject></mediaobject></screenshot></figure>
	<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

	<para> The top of the window shows the dialog title including the name
	of the person whose attribute is being edited. The central part 
	of the window displays three notebook tabs containing different 
	categories of available information. You can bring any tab to the 
	top for viewing or editing by clicking on the appropriate tab heading. 
	The bottom part has <guibutton>OK</guibutton> and 
	<guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> buttons. Clicking the 
	<guibutton>OK</guibutton> button at any time will apply all the 
	changes made in all tabs and close the dialog window. Clicking the 
	<guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> button at any time will close the window without 
	applying any changes. </para> 
	
	<tip><para>
    The tab labels reflect the presence of corresponding information: if the 
    tab contains any data, its label appears boldface; if the tab has no data
    then its label appears regular (not bold). </para></tip>
    
    <para>The tabs provide the following information categories of 
	the attribute data: </para>

 	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>General</guilabel></term>
		<listitem><para>The 
	<guilabel>General</guilabel> tab allows editing of the most general
	information about the attribute: name of the attribute and its value. 
	The information can be typed in the appropriate text entry fields. 
	The attribute name can also be selected from available choices (if any) 
	listed in the <guilabel>Attribute </guilabel> drop-down menu. 
	Check the <guilabel>Private record</guilabel> box to mark this 
	attribute record as private. This will give you a chance to omit 
	this attribute from being included in the reports, if you choose 
	so among the report generation options. </para>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Sources</guilabel></term>
		<listitem><para>The 
	<guilabel>Sources</guilabel> tab displays information about sources 
	relevant to this attribute and controls allowing its modification. 
	The central part displays the list of all such sources references 
	stored in the database. The buttons <guibutton>+</guibutton>, 
	<guibutton>Edit</guibutton>, and <guibutton>-</guibutton> 
	allow you to correspondingly add, modify, and remove a source reference  
	to this attribute. Note that the <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> and 
	<guibutton>-</guibutton> buttons become available only when 
	a source reference is selected from the list. </para>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Note</guilabel></term>
		<listitem>
	<para>The <guilabel>Note</guilabel> tab displays any notes concerning 
	the attribute. To add a note or modify existing notes simply edit the 
	text in the text entry field.
	</para>

    <para>The <guilabel>Format</guilabel> option allows you to set the 
    appearance of the note in the output (i.e. in reports and web pages). 
    Selecting 
    <guilabel>Flowed</guilabel> will replace all multiple spaces, tabs, 
    and single end-of-line characters with single space in the output. 
    The two consecutive new lines (i.e. an empty line) denote a new paragraph.
    Selecting <guilabel>Preformatted</guilabel> will honor all multiple spaces
    tabs, and new lines, so that the output will appear as it is entered
    into the text entry field. 
	</para>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
      </sect2>
      
      <!-- ================ Usage Sub-subsection ================ -->
      <sect2 id="adv-ad"> 
        <title>Addresses</title> 
	<para> Addresses are edited through the following 
	<guilabel>Address Editor</guilabel> dialog: </para>

 	<!-- ==== Figure: Address Editor dialog ==== -->
	<figure id="edit-ad-fig"> 
	<title>Address Editor dialog</title> 
	<screenshot><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata 
		fileref="figures/edit-ad.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	<textobject> 
	<phrase>Shows Address Editor dialog. </phrase>
	</textobject></mediaobject></screenshot></figure>
	<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->
	
	<para> The top of the window shows the dialog title including the name
	of the person whose address is being edited. The central part 
	of the window displays three notebook tabs containing different 
	categories of available information. You can bring any tab to the 
	top for viewing or editing by clicking on the appropriate tab heading. 
	The bottom part has <guibutton>OK</guibutton> and 
	<guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> buttons. Clicking the 
	<guibutton>OK</guibutton> button at any time will apply all the 
	changes made in all tabs and close the dialog window. Clicking the 
	<guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> button at any time will close the window without 
	applying any changes. </para> 
	
	<tip><para>
    The tab labels reflect the presence of corresponding information: if the 
    tab contains any data, its label appears boldface; if the tab has no data
    then its label appears regular (not bold).</para></tip> 
    
    <para>The tabs provide the following information categories of 
	the address data: </para>

 	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>General</guilabel></term>
		<listitem><para>The 
	<guilabel>General</guilabel> tab allows editing of the most general
	information about the address: date, street address, city or county, 
	state or province, country, the postal code, and the phone number. 
    The information can 
	be typed in the appropriate text entry fields. 
	Check the <guilabel>Private record</guilabel> box to mark this address 
	record as private. This will give you a chance to omit this address 
	from being included in reports, if you choose so among the report 
	generation options. </para>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Sources</guilabel></term>
		<listitem><para>The 
	<guilabel>Sources</guilabel> tab displays information about sources 
	relevant to this address and controls allowing its modification. 
	The central part displays the list of all such sources references 
	stored in the database. The buttons <guibutton>+</guibutton>, 
	<guibutton>Edit</guibutton>, and <guibutton>-</guibutton> 
	allow you to correspondingly add, modify, and remove a source reference  
	to this address. Note that the <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> and 
	<guibutton>-</guibutton> buttons become available only when 
	a source reference is selected from the list. </para>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Note</guilabel></term>
		<listitem>
	<para>The <guilabel>Note</guilabel> tab displays any notes concerning 
	the address. To add a note or modify existing notes simply edit the 
	text in the text entry field.
	</para>

    <para>The <guilabel>Format</guilabel> option allows you to set the 
    appearance of the note in the output (i.e. in reports and web pages). 
    Selecting 
    <guilabel>Flowed</guilabel> will replace all multiple spaces, tabs, 
    and single end-of-line characters with single space in the output. 
    The two consecutive new lines (i.e. an empty line) denote a new paragraph.
    Selecting <guilabel>Preformatted</guilabel> will honor all multiple spaces
    tabs, and new lines, so that the output will appear as it is entered
    into the text entry field. 
	</para>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

      </sect2>
      
      <!-- ================ Usage Sub-subsection ================ -->
      <sect2 id="adv-wit"> 
        <title>Witnesses</title> 
	<para> Witnesses are edited through the following 
	<guilabel>Witness Editor</guilabel> dialog: </para>

 	<!-- ==== Figure: Witness Editor dialog ==== -->
	<figure id="edit-wi-fig"> 
	<title>Witness Editor dialog</title> 
	<screenshot><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata 
		fileref="figures/edit-wi.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	<textobject> 
	<phrase>Shows Witness Editor dialog. </phrase>
	</textobject></mediaobject></screenshot></figure>
	<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->
	
	<para> The top of the window shows the dialog title. The central part 
	of the window displays information about the witness. The bottom part 
	has <guibutton>OK</guibutton> and <guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> buttons. 
	Clicking the <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button at any time will apply all the 
	changes made and close the dialog window. Clicking the 
	<guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> button at any time will close the window 
	without applying any changes. </para> 
	
	<para>The witness name can be entered in two ways, depending upon 
	whether the witness is a person already stored in the database or 
	not (unrelated person). </para> 

    <tip><para>If the person you would like to add as a wittness is in fact
	a member of the database, it is better to use the first method below.
    </para></tip>
	
	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term>Person from the database</term>
		<listitem><para> 
	If the person's data are stored in a database, check <guilabel>Person 
	is in the database</guilabel> box. Then click the 
        <guibutton>Select</guibutton> button to evoke <guilabel>Select
        Person</guilabel> dialog. Choose the person from that dialog and 
        click the <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button. The <guilabel>Person</guilabel> 
        text field will display the name of the person you selected. 
	</para>
    
    <note><para>Even though the person's name is displayed in the 
        <guilabel>Person</guilabel> field, it is not available for direct
        editing. </para></note>
    </listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
	
	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term>Unrelated person</term>
		<listitem><para> 
	If the person is not in the database, make sure that 
	<guilabel>Person is in the database</guilabel> box is unchecked. 
	Then enter the name or any description of a person into the
	<guilabel>Person</guilabel> text entry field. This information 
	is stored as entered, and this is the only place it is stored.
	In other words, there is no reference to that person in the entire 
	database except for this witness reference. If the person is in fact
	a member of the database, it is advised to use the former method.
	</para>
		</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
	
	<para> The <guilabel>Comment</guilabel> text area allows you to enter 
	any comments concerning the witness. To add a comment or to modify 
	existing comments simply edit the text in the text area.
	</para>

      </sect2>
      
       <!-- ================ Usage Sub-subsection ================ -->
      <sect2 id="adv-merge"><title>Merging records</title>

	<para> Sometime several records in the database turn out to be 
        describing the same object: same person, same place, or same source.
	It could happen either when the data is entered twice by mistake,
	or when new information reveals that the two entries refer to the same
	person. It can also happen after importing GEDCOM obtained from a
	relative, whose database overlaps with your existing data.</para>
	
	<para>Whenever you detect duplicate records, merging them
        a useful way of correcting the situation. </para>
	
        <tip><para> To make a merge, exactly two records have to be selected
	in the appropriate view (People View, Sources View, or Places View).
	This is accomplished by selecting one entry and then
        selecting another person while holding down <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key.
        </para></tip>

        <sect3 id="adv-merge-people"><title>Merge People</title> 
	<para> There are two ways of merging personal records: 
	<guilabel>Compare and Merge</guilabel> and
	<guilabel>Fast Merge</guilabel>, both available from the 
	<guimenu>Edit</guimenu> menu.
	</para>
        
	<note><para>
	Merging people does not discard any information with either method.
	The decisions you make during the merge only affect which data will
	become primary and which will become secondary for the resulting
	merged record.
	</para></note>


	<variablelist>
	<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Compare and Merge</guilabel></term>
	<listitem><para>
        When exactly two people are selected, choose
        <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Compare and
	Merge...</guimenuitem></menuchoice> to evoke <guilabel>Compare
	People</guilabel> dialog.</para>
	
 	<!-- ==== Figure: Compare People dialog ==== -->
	<figure id="comp-people-fig"> 
	<title>Compare People dialog</title> 
	<screenshot><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata 
		fileref="figures/comp-people.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	<textobject> 
	<phrase>Shows Compare People dialog. </phrase>
	</textobject></mediaobject></screenshot></figure>
	<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

	<para>The dialog allows you to make a decision on whether or not
	the selected records should be merged. If you decide that the records
	should not be merged, despite similar names, you may click
	<guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> to close the dialog without making
	any changes. If you decide to proceed with merging, select the 
	appropriate <guilabel>Select</guilabel> radio button to specify
	the record to be used as the source of primary data,
	then click <guibutton>Merge and close</guibutton>. </para>
	
        <para>The data from the other record will be kept as alternate
        data. Specifically, all names from the other record will become
	alternate names of the merged record. Similarly, parents, spouses,
	and children of the other record will become alternate parents,
	spouses, and children of the merged record, and so on.
	</para></listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	<variablelist>
	<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Fast Merge</guilabel></term>
	<listitem><para>
        When exactly two people are selected, choose
        <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Fast
	Merge</guimenuitem></menuchoice> to evoke <guilabel>Merge
	People</guilabel> dialog.</para>
	
 	<!-- ==== Figure: Compare People dialog ==== -->
	<figure id="merge-people-fig"> 
	<title>Merge People dialog</title> 
	<screenshot><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata 
		fileref="figures/merge-people.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	<textobject> 
	<phrase>Shows Merge People dialog. </phrase>
	</textobject></mediaobject></screenshot></figure>
	<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

	<para>The dialog allows you to quickly merge two records, specifying
	the record to be used as the source of primary data.
	The data from the other record will be kept as alternate
        data. Specifically, all names from the other record will become
	alternate names of the merged record. Similarly, parents, spouses,
	and children of the other record will become alternate parents,
	spouses, and children of the merged record, and so on.
	</para>
	
	<tip><para>If you are not certain whether or not you need
	to merge the records, or which record to specify as the source
	of primary data, use <guilabel>Compare and Merge</guilabel> method
	described above..
	</para></tip>

	</listitem></varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
      </sect3>

       <!-- ================ Usage Sub-subsection ================ -->
      <sect3 id="adv-merge-sources"> 
        <title>Merge Sources</title> 
	<para>When exactly two sources are selected, choose
        <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Compare and
	Merge...</guimenuitem></menuchoice> to evoke <guilabel>Merge
	Sources</guilabel> dialog.</para>
	
 	<!-- ==== Figure: Merge Sources dialog ==== -->
	<figure id="merge-src-fig"> 
	<title>Merge Sources dialog</title> 
	<screenshot><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata 
		fileref="figures/merge-src.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	<textobject> 
	<phrase>Shows Merge Sources dialog. </phrase>
	</textobject></mediaobject></screenshot></figure>
	<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

	<para>The dialog allows you to make a decision on whether or not
	the selected records should be merged. If you decide that the records
	should not be merged, despite similar titles, you may click
	<guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> to close the dialog without making
	any changes. If you decide to proceed with merging, choose the 
	appropriate radio button to specify the title, author, abbreviated
	title, publication information, and the ID to be used for the
	merged record, then click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>. </para>
	
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="adv-merge-places"> 
        <title>Merge Places</title> 

	<para>When exactly two places are selected, choose
        <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Compare and
	Merge...</guimenuitem></menuchoice> to evoke <guilabel>Select
	title</guilabel> dialog.</para>
	
 	<!-- ==== Figure: Select title dialog ==== -->
	<figure id="merge-plc-fig"> 
	<title>Merge Places dialog</title> 
	<screenshot><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata 
		fileref="figures/merge-plc.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	<textobject> 
	<phrase>Shows Select title dialog. </phrase>
	</textobject></mediaobject></screenshot></figure>
	<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

	<para>The dialog allows you to make a decision on whether or not
	the selected records should be merged. If you decide that the records
	should not be merged, despite similar titles, you may click
	<guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> to close the dialog without making
	any changes. If you decide to proceed with merging, choose the 
	appropriate radio button to specify the title of the merged record,
	or specify <guilabel>Other</guilabel> and enter new text,
	then click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>. </para>
      </sect3>

      </sect2>

   </sect1>

    <!-- ================ Usage Subsection ================================ -->
    <sect1 id="gramps-nav"> 
       <title>Navigation</title> 
	<para> As long as any database is open, &app; is focused on a 
	single person usually referred to as an Active person. This 
	allows you to view or modify the data concerning this person, 
	his or her immediate family, etc. Navigating in the database (i.e. 
	moving from person to person) is in fact nothing else but changing 
	the Active person. This section describes many alternative ways
	to navigate through the database using both the complex and the 
        convenient interfaces &app; provides. All these ways eventually 
        accomplish the same thing, but some are more convenient than others, 
        depending what you are doing in &app; at the moment. </para>
       
      <!-- ================ Usage Sub-subsection ================ -->
      <sect2 id="gramps-nav-people"> 
        <title>Using the People View </title> 
	<para> The most intuitive way to select an active person is 
	to use the People View (see <xref linkend="people-view"/>). 
        When in the People View, just select the 
	name of the desired person from the list by clicking that list 
	entry. The person you have selected becomes active. The statusbar 
	updates to reflect the change of the active person. </para> 
      </sect2>

      <!-- ================ Usage Sub-subsection ================ -->
      <sect2 id="gramps-nav-family"> 
        <title>Using the Family View</title> 
	<para> When in the Family View (see <xref linkend="family-view"/>), 
        you can easily navigate between the members of the displayed family 
        as follows: </para>

	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>To make the currently selected spouse the active person, 
	click the double-arrow button to the right of the active person box. 
        Alternatively, right-click into the spouse box and select 
        <guilabel>Make the selected spouse an active person</guilabel> item 
        from the context menu. 
	</para></listitem>
	
	<listitem><para>To make the currently selected parents the active family
	(thereby making father the active person and mother the selected
	spouse), click the right-arrow button to the right of the active person's
	parents box. Alternatively, right-click into the active person's parents 
        box and select 
        <guilabel>Make the selected parents the active family</guilabel> item 
        from the context menu. 
        </para></listitem> 
	
	<listitem><para>To make the currently selected spouse's parents 
	the active family (thereby making father the active person and mother 
	the selected spouse), click the right-arrow button to the right of the 
	spouse's parents box. Alternatively, right-click into the spouse's parents 
        box and select 
        <guilabel>Make the selected parents the active family</guilabel> item 
        from the context menu. </para></listitem>
	
	<listitem><para>To make the currently selected child the active person, 
	click the left-arrow button to the right of the children box. 
        Alternatively, right-click into the children box and select 
        <guilabel>Make the selected child an active person</guilabel> item 
        from the context menu.
	</para></listitem>

	</itemizedlist>

        <para>In addition to this, &app; provides an extensive set of keyboard
        navigation options. The detailed reference to the keybindings 
        is found in the <xref linkend="append-keybind"/>.</para>

      </sect2>

      <!-- ================ Usage Sub-subsection ================ -->
      <sect2 id="gramps-nav-pedigree"> 
        <title>Using the Pedigree View</title> 
	<para> The Pedigree View (see <xref linkend="pedigree-view"/>) also 
        allows you to move along the family tree. 
	The benefit of this method is that you can see more than one 
	generation of the family tree. Also, you can jump directly from a
	great-grandson to a great-grandfather without going through the 
	intermediate generations. </para>

	<para> Note that after changing the active person in the Pedigree 
	View, the display is re-adjusted to show four generations, starting 
	from the newly selected Active person. When in the Pedigree View, you 
	can easily navigate between the members of the displayed family tree 
	as follows: </para> 

	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>To make any displayed person the active person, 
	double-click the line that connects to the left side of the
	corresponding box. </para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>To make a child of the currently active person (if any) 
	the active person, click the left arrow button to the left of the
	corresponding box. If there is more than one child, the button expands
	to the menu listing the children to choose from. </para></listitem> 

	<listitem><para>To move the whole family tree one generation back,
	click on the corresponding right arrow button on the right-hand side 
	of the display area. Clicking the upper button will move the tree 
	along the paternal line. Clicking the lower button will move the 
	tree along the maternal line. </para>

	<para> Clicking either of these buttons is completely equivalent to
	double-clicking the lines connecting to the left of the corresponding
	boxes for father and mother. </para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	
	<para>You can also quickly access any of the spouses, siblings,
	children, or parents of any displayed person. To do this, move the
	mouse over the desired person's box and right-click to invoke
	a context menu. The appropriate menu items will contain submenus
	listing all spouses, siblings, children, and parents of the
	corresponding person. 
	</para>
	
	<tip><title>Advantages of using right-click menus</title>
	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>Direct access to spouse and siblings</para></listitem> 
	<listitem><para>Complete lists of all member of all categories,
	not only the preferred members.</para></listitem> 
	</itemizedlist>
	
	</tip>

      </sect2>

      <!-- ================ Usage Sub-subsection ================ -->
      <sect2 id="gramps-nav-default"> 
        <title>Setting the Home Person</title> 
	<para> One and only one person in the database can be selected as the 
	Home person. Once the Home person is selected, moving to that
	person becomes a matter of a single click, regardless of which view 
	you are using at the moment. </para>

	<para> To set the Home person, first navigate to that person using 
	any method you like. Then choose 
	<menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
	<guimenuitem>Set Home person</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. Once this is 
	done, you can move to the Home person from anywhere in the 
	database by simply clicking the <guibutton>Home</guibutton> icon 
        on the toolbar. You can also choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Go</guimenu>
	<guimenuitem>Home</guimenuitem></menuchoice> from the menu or select 
        <guilabel>Home</guilabel> item from any context menu available on the 
        right click. 
        </para>
	
      </sect2>


      <!-- ================ Usage Sub-subsection ================ -->
      <sect2 id="gramps-nav-history"> 
        <title>Using history-based tools</title> 
	<para> &app; also features a powerful set of history-based navigation 
        tools. These tools are similar to those commonly used in web browsers. 
        They include <guilabel>Back</guilabel> and <guilabel>Forward</guilabel>
        items available from the <menuchoice><guimenu>Go</guimenu></menuchoice> 
        menu, context menus (available in People, Family, and Pedigree views),
	and the toolbar buttons. They also include the list of the recent
	selections available under the 
	<menuchoice><guimenu>Go</guimenu></menuchoice> menu that allows you
	to jump directly to any of the recent selections. 
        Finally, right-clicking on the <guibutton>Back</guibutton> 
        and <guibutton>Forward</guibutton> toolbar buttons invokes the 
        popup menu with corresponding portion of the history. Select any item
        from the menu to jump directly to it. </para>

      </sect2>

      <!-- ================ Usage Sub-subsection ================ -->
      <sect2 id="gramps-nav-bookmk"> 
        <title>Bookmarking People</title> 
	<para> Similar to setting the Home person, you can bookmark other 
        people from the database to simplify further navigation. To bookmark 
        a person, first navigate to that person, then choose 
	<menuchoice><guimenu>Bookmarks</guimenu>
	<guimenuitem>Add bookmark</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. To move to that
	person from anywhere in the database, choose 
	<menuchoice><guimenu>Bookmarks</guimenu>
	<guisubmenu>Go to bookmark</guisubmenu>
	<guimenuitem><replaceable>Person's name</replaceable></guimenuitem>
	</menuchoice>. </para>
	
	<para> You can manage your bookmarks by choosing 
	<menuchoice><guimenu>Bookmarks</guimenu>
	<guimenuitem>Edit bookmarks...</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. This opens
	the following <guilabel>Edit Bookmarks</guilabel> dialog with the 
	list of	bookmarks and the controls to modify this list. </para>
	
 	<!-- ==== Figure: Edit Bookmarks dialog ==== -->
	<figure id="edit-bm-fig"> 
	<title>Edit Bookmarks dialog</title> 
	<screenshot><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata 
		fileref="figures/edit-bm.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	<textobject> 
	<phrase>Shows Edit Bookmarks dialog. </phrase>
	</textobject></mediaobject></screenshot></figure>
	<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

      </sect2>

      <!-- ================ Usage Sub-subsection ================ -->
      <sect2 id="gramps-nav-find">
      <title>Finding records</title>

	<para>To find a record in a database, first switch to the appripriate
	View that provides the list of the desired records: People, Sources,
	Places, or Media. Then start typing the name of a person or the title
	of a Source, Place, or Media object that you are looking for,
	respectively.
	You may also press <keycap>Ctrl+F</keycap> to turn on the search
	mode, but simply staring to type is also enough.</para>
	
 	<!-- ==== Figure: Type-ahead find ==== -->
	<figure id="find-people-fig"> 
	<title>Type-ahead find</title> 
	<screenshot><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata 
		fileref="figures/find-people.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	<textobject> 
	<phrase>Shows type-ahead find. </phrase>
	</textobject></mediaobject></screenshot></figure>
	<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

	<para> As you type, the first record in the list that is compatible
	with your input will be selected.</para>

	<tip>
        <title>Finding People</title> 
	<para>For more complex people searches you may want to use filters.
	Enable filter controls by choosing <menuchoice><guimenu>View</guimenu> 
	<guimenuitem>Filter</guimenuitem> </menuchoice>, select the desired
	filter, and click <guibutton>Apply</guibutton>.
	For details, see <xref linkend="filters"/></para></tip>

     </sect2>

   </sect1>
   
    <!-- ================ Usage Subsection ================================ -->
    <sect1 id="gen-reports"> 
        <title>Generating Reports</title> 
	<para> Reports are the most common form of the output produced by
	genealogical research. The majority of genealogical software puts a lot
	of emphasis on developing nicely looking reports. &app; is no 
	exception in this regard: it offers a choice of a variety of reports. 
	&app; can generate reports in a multitude of open formats, both 
	text based and graphical. &app; can also produce screen based reports 
	that are convenient for viewing a summary of your database. 
	Finally, &app; can generate a web site suitable for immediate 
	posting on the Internet. All these are almost infinitely flexible: 
        if you wish to modify or extend the default format of &app; report 
	you can design and choose the style for each of your reports. </para>

	<para> All reports can be accessed through the menu by choosing
	<menuchoice><guimenu>Reports</guimenu>
	<guisubmenu><replaceable>Report Type</replaceable></guisubmenu>
	<guimenuitem><replaceable>Particular 
	Report</replaceable></guimenuitem></menuchoice>. Alternatively, 
	you can browse the complete selection of available reports along 
	with their brief descriptions in a <guilabel>Report 
	Selection</guilabel> dialog evoked by clicking the 
	<guibutton>Reports</guibutton> icon on the toolbar. 
	</para>


      <!-- =============== Usage Sub-subsection ================ -->
      <sect2 id="rep-graph"> 
	<title>Graphical Reports</title> 
	<para> Graphical reports represent information in forms of charts 
	and graphs. Most of the options are common among graphical reports, 
	therefore they will be described only once, at the end of this 
	section. The few options which are specific to a given report will be 
	described directly in that report's entry.</para>

	<para>The following graphical reports are currently 
	available in &app;: </para>
	
	<variablelist>

	<varlistentry><term>Ancestor Chart</term>
	<listitem><para>This report generates the chart of people who are
	ancestors of the Active person. Specific options include 
	the number of generations considered and the format of the displayed 
	entries. </para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term>Ancestor Chart (Wall Chart)</term>
	<listitem><para>This report is similar to the Ancestor Chart report. 
    It provides more options which make it useful for generating huge charts
    suitable for a poster or a wall chart. These options include the ability
    to compress the report (getting rid of an empty space) and the option
    to fit the whole chart onto a single page. In the latter case, the
    contents of the chart is scaled down appropriately. </para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term>Descendant Graph</term>
	<listitem><para>This report generates a graph of people who are
	descendants of the Active person. Specific options include 
	the format of the displayed entries. </para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term>Relationship Graph</term>
	<listitem><para>This report creates a complex relationship graph in 
	GraphViz format. The GraphViz <command>dot</command> tool can 
	transform the graph into postscript, jpeg, png, vrml, svg, and many
	other formats. GraphViz tools are freely available from the 
	<ulink url="http://www.graphviz.org" type="http">GraphViz 
	site</ulink>. Specific options for this report 
	include filter and number of generations considered, as well as 
	several GraphViz-specific options related to pagination, color, 
	and details of the graph. </para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term>Timeline Graph</term>
	<listitem><para>This report outputs the list of people with their
	lifetimes represented by intervals on a common chronological scale. 
	Specific options include filter, sorting method, and the title of 
	the report. </para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	</variablelist>

	<para>Common options for graphical reports are the filename of the
	output, the format of the output, selected style, page size and 
	orientation. Optionally, the reports can be immediately opened
    with the default application (set in the main GNOME 
    <menuchoice><guimenu>Desktop Preferenes</guimenu>
    <guisubmenu><replaceable>Advanced</replaceable></guisubmenu>
	<guimenuitem><replaceable>Preferred 
    Applications</replaceable></guimenuitem></menuchoice> dialog). 
    </para>

      </sect2>

      <!-- =============== Usage Sub-subsection ================ -->
      <sect2 id="rep-text"> 
	<title>Text Reports</title> 
	<para> Text reports represent the desired information as formatted 
	text. Most of the options are common among text reports, 
	therefore they will be described only once, at the end of this 
	section. The options which are specific to a given report will be 
	described directly in that report's entry.</para>
	
	<para>The following text reports are currently 
	available in &app;:</para>

	<variablelist>

	<varlistentry><term>Ahnentafel Report</term>
	<listitem><para>This report lists the active person and his or her 
	ancestors along with their vital data. The people are numbered in a 
	special way which is an established standard called Ahnentafel. 
	The active person is given number 1. His or her father and mother 
	have numbers 2 and 3, respectively. This rule holds for every person 
	while going back in generations: father's parents are numbered 4 and 5, 
	and mother's parents are numbered 6 and 7, fathers always numbered 
	with even and mothers with odd numbers. Therefore, for any person 
	having number N in this tree, the numbers of father and mother 
	are 2N and 2N+1, respectively. 
	</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term>Comprehensive Ancestors Report</term>
	<listitem><para>This report produces a comprehensive description 
	of ancestors of the active person. The highlights of this report
        include elaborate layout, images of children, present and former 
        spouses, and source citations. Specific options: number 
	of backward generations to consider, whether to cite sources, 
        and whether to break pages between generations. </para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term>Complete Individual Report</term>
	<listitem><para>This report provides individual summaries similar to
	that of the Individual Summary report. The advantage of this report 
	is the specific filter option. Depending on the filter choice (active
	person only, his or her descendants, his or her ancestors, or entire
	database), the report may contain from one to many individual 
	summaries. Another option for this report is the inclusion of 
	source information when listing events. </para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term>Descendant Report</term>
	<listitem><para>This report produces a brief description 
	of descendants of the active person. Specific options: number 
	of forward generations to consider. </para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term>Detailed Ancestral Report</term>
	<listitem><para>This report covers in detail the ancestors of the
	active person. It includes vital data (birth and death) as well as 
	marriages. Specific options: number of backward generations 
	to consider, as well as a variety of options regarding the exact 
	contents to include. </para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term>Detailed Descendant Report</term>
	<listitem><para>This report covers in detail the descendants of the
	active person. It includes vital (birth and death) information as well as 
	marriages. Specific options: number of forward generations 
	to consider. </para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term>FTM Style Ancestral Report</term>
	<listitem><para>This report creates an ancestral report similar to 
        that produced by the Family Tree Maker (tm) program. It covers in detail the 
        active person and his/her ancestors It includes vital information 
        as well as marriages, children, and notes.  Specific options: number 
        of backward generations to consider. </para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term>FTM Style Descendant Report</term>
	<listitem><para>This report creates a descendant report similar to 
        that produced by the Family Tree Maker (tm) program. It covers in detail the 
        active person and his/her descendants. It includes vital information 
        as well as marriages, children, and notes. Specific options: 
        number of forward generations to consider. </para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term>Family Group Report</term>
	<listitem><para>This creates a family group report, showing
	information on a set of parents and their children. Specific 
	options: the spouse (available only if the active person has more
	than one spouse). </para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term>Individual Summary</term>
	<listitem><para>This report produces a detailed summary on the 
	active person. The report includes all the facts known to the 
	database about that person. </para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	</variablelist>

	<para>Common options for text reports are the filename of the
	output, the format of the output, selected style, page size and 
	orientation. For HTML reports, there is no page information. 
	Instead, HTML options include the choice of the HTML template, 
	either available in &app; or a custom template defined by you. 
    Optionally, the reports can be immediately opened
    with the default application (set in the main GNOME 
    <menuchoice><guimenu>Desktop Preferenes</guimenu>
    <guisubmenu><replaceable>Advanced</replaceable></guisubmenu>
	<guimenuitem><replaceable>Preferred 
    Applications</replaceable></guimenuitem></menuchoice> dialog). 
    </para>

      </sect2>

      <!-- =============== Usage Sub-subsection ================ -->
      <sect2 id="rep-books"> 
	<title>Books</title> 
	<para> Currently, the only available report under this category
        is the Book Report. </para>

	<para> The Book Report creates a single document (i.e. a Book) 
        containing a collection of graphical and textual reports.
        Consequently, this allows for a very rich set of documents 
        that &app; can produce. 
        </para>

	<para> When Book Report is selected, the following book configuration
        dialog appears: </para>

 	<!-- ==== Figure: Book Report dialog ==== -->
	<figure id="rep-book-fig"> 
	<title>Book Report dialog</title> 
	<screenshot><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata 
		fileref="figures/bookreport.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	<textobject> 
	<phrase>Shows Book Report dialog. </phrase>
	</textobject></mediaobject></screenshot></figure>
	<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

	<para> The <guilabel>Book name</guilabel> text entry field is used to
        save the book (a set of configured selections) for future use.
        The top pane lists the items available for inclusion in the 
        book. The bottom pane lists the currently selected items in
        the order they will appear in the book. </para>
        
	<para> The horizontal set of buttons by the <guilabel>Book 
	name</guilabel> field operates on the whole book. Click 
	the <guibutton>Clear</guibutton> button to clear all items from
        the current book. Click the <guibutton>Save</guibutton> button to 
	save the current book (under the name typed in 
	the <guilabel>Book name</guilabel> text entry field) for future use. 
	Note that saving the book also saves the configuration for each item. 
	Click the <guibutton>Open</guibutton> button to load
        the book from the list of previously saved books. Finally, click the 
        <guibutton>Edit books</guibutton> button to evoke the editable list of
        available books.  </para>
	
	<para> The vertical set of buttons to the right of the bottom pane
	operates on the 
	selected book item. Click the <guibutton>Add</guibutton> button to 
	add selected item from the available list to the current book. Click 
	the <guibutton>Remove</guibutton> button to remove an item from the 
	current book. Use <guibutton>Up</guibutton> and 
	<guibutton>Down</guibutton> to change the items order in the current 
	book. Click the <guibutton>Setup</guibutton> button to configure the 
	options of the selected item of the current book. 
        </para>

	<para> The configuration dialogs evoked by <guibutton>Setup</guibutton>
        are item-specific. If you choose not to configure the item, sane
        defaults will be used for all needed options. The common option for 
        almost all book items is the center person: the person on whom the
        item is centered. Thanks to this option, you can create a book with
        items centered on different people (e.g. your mom's and dad's 
        ancestors as separate chapters). By default, the center person is 
	set to the active person. </para> 

	<para>Almost all items available for inclusion in the book are textual 
        or graphical reports, and are therefore available in the form of standalone 
        reports. The exception is the following items which are only available as 
        book items:</para>

	<variablelist>

	<varlistentry><term>Title Page</term>
	<listitem><para>This item produces a customized Title page. You can 
        configure the text of title, subtitle, and the footer of the page. 
        An image can be optionally placed between the subtitle and the footer. 
        Because of its configurability, this item can be used to create 
        title pages for the whole book, its chapter, or even a single item. 
        </para>
        </listitem>
	</varlistentry>

 	<varlistentry><term>Custom Text</term>
	<listitem><para>This item produces a page with three paragraphs, each 
        containing custom text. The appearance of the text can be adjusted by 
        using custom styles. This item was meant to be used for epigraphs, 
        dedications, explanations, notes, and so forth. 
        </para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	</variablelist>

      </sect2>

      <!-- =============== Usage Sub-subsection ================ -->
      <sect2 id="rep-view"> 
	<title>View Reports</title> 
	<para> View reports represent overall summaries of the database 
	information available immediately for on-screen viewing. 
	The following view reports are currently available in &app;:</para>

	<variablelist>

	<varlistentry><term>Number of ancestors</term>
	<listitem><para>This report displays the number of ancestors of the
	active person. </para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

 	<varlistentry><term>Summary of the database</term>
	<listitem><para>This report displays the overall statistics concerning
	number of individuals of each gender, various incomplete entries
	statistics, as well as family and media statistics. </para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	</variablelist>
     </sect2>

      <!-- =============== Usage Sub-subsection ================ -->
      <sect2 id="rep-web"> 
	<title>Web Page</title> 

	<para> This report generates web pages, either for a selected 
	individual (active person) or a set of individuals. The options 
	for this report are broken down into contents, privacy, and advanced 
	options. The contents options include the filter (determine the 
	scope of the database to consider), 
	destination directory for the images, an optional short ancestor tree, 
        and a link to the index page.
	Privacy options allow you to omit private records, restrict 
	information on living people, skip images (either all or only 
        those of living people), and omit comments and text in source 
        information. Finally, the advanced options allow you to include 
        the optional &app; ID, create a GENDEX index, and specify the 
        extension of the resulting files. </para>

      </sect2>

   </sect1>

    <!-- ================ Usage Subsection ================================ -->
    <sect1 id="gramps-tools"> 
        <title>Running Tools</title> 
	<para> &app; tools allow you to perform various types of analyses
	of your genealogical data. Typically, the tools do not produce 
	output in form of printouts or files. Instead, they produce screen
	output immediately available for the researcher. However, when
	appropriate, you can save the results of running a tool into a file. 
	Tools present one of the major strengths of &app; compared to the most
	genealogical software. </para> 
	
	<para>The tools can be accessed through the menu by choosing 
	<menuchoice><guimenu>Tools</guimenu>
	<guisubmenu><replaceable>Tool Section</replaceable></guisubmenu>
	<guimenuitem><replaceable>Particular 
	Tool</replaceable></guimenuitem></menuchoice>. Alternatively, 
	you can browse the complete selection of available tools along 
	with their brief descriptions in a <guilabel>Tool 
	Selection</guilabel> dialog evoked by clicking the 
	<guibutton>Tools</guibutton> icon on the toolbar. </para>

      <!-- =============== Usage Sub-subsection ================ -->
      <sect2 id="tools-ae"> 
	<title>Analysis and Exploration</title> 
	<para> This section contains tools which analyze and explore the
	database, but do not alter it. The following analysis and exploration
	tools are currently available in &app;: </para>

	<variablelist>

	<varlistentry><term>Compare individual events</term>
	<listitem><para>This tool compares events across the selected group of
	people. The people for this comparison are chosen with the use of 
	custom filters. The custom filters can be created in the Custom Filter
	Editor (see <xref linkend="tools-util"/>). The resulting table produced
	by this tool can be saved as a spreadsheet. </para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

 	<varlistentry><term>Interactive descendant browser</term>
	<listitem><para>This tool builds a tree with the active person being 
	the root. Children branch from their parents in the usual manner. 
	Use this tool for a quick glance of a person's descendants. 
	</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	</variablelist>
      </sect2>

      <!-- =============== Usage Sub-subsection ================ -->
      <sect2 id="tools-db"> 
	<title>Database Processing</title> 
	<para> This section contains tools which may modify your database. 
	The modifications will only be performed upon your explicit consent. 
	The tools from this section are used mostly for finding and correcting
	errors in the data. The following database processing tools are 
	currently available in &app;:</para>

	<variablelist>

 	<varlistentry><term>Check and repair database</term>
	<listitem><para>This tool checks the database for integrity problems, 
	fixing the problems it can. Specifically, the tool is checking for:</para>
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para>Broken family links. These are the cases when 
		a person's record refers to a family while the family's record 
		does not refer to that person, and vice versa.
		</para></listitem>

		<listitem><para>Missing media objects. The missing media 
		object is the object whose file is referenced in the database 
		but does not exist. This can happen when the file is 
		accidentally deleted, renamed, or moved to another location.
		</para></listitem>

		<listitem><para>Empty families. These are the family entries 
		which have no reference to any person as their member. 
		</para></listitem>

		<listitem><para>Parent relationship. This checks all families
		to ensure that father and mother are not mixed up. The check 
		is also made that parents have different gender. If they have 
		common gender then their relationship is renamed to "Partners".
		</para></listitem>

	</itemizedlist>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>

 	<varlistentry><term>Extract information from names</term>
	<listitem><para>This tool searches the entire database and attempts 
	to extract titles and nicknames that may be embedded in a person's 
	<guilabel>Given name</guilabel> field. 
	</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

 	<varlistentry><term>Find possible duplicate people</term>
	<listitem><para>This tool searches the entire database, looking 
	for the entries that may represent the same person. 
	</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

 	<varlistentry><term>Rename personal event types</term>
	<listitem><para>This tool allows all the events of a certain name
	to be renamed to a new name. 
	</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

 	<varlistentry><term>Reorder &app; IDs</term>
	<listitem><para>This tool reorders the &app; IDs according to the
	defaults of &app;.
	</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	</variablelist>

      </sect2>

      <!-- =============== Usage Sub-subsection ================ -->
      <sect2 id="tools-util"> 
	<title>Utilities</title> 
	<para> </para>

 	<para> This section contains tools allowing you to perform a simple 
	operation on a portion of data. The results can be saved in your
	database, but they will not modify your existing data. 
	The following utilities are currently available in &app;:</para>

	<variablelist>

 	<varlistentry><term>Custom Filter Editor</term>
	<listitem><para>The Custom Filter Editor builds custom filters 
	that can be used to select people included in reports, exports, 
	and other tools and utilities. This is in fact a very powerful tool 
	in genealogical analysis.</para> 
	
	<para>When you launch it, the <guilabel>User defined filters</guilabel> 
	dialog appears that lists all the filters (if any) previously defined 
	by you. Click the <guibutton>Add...</guibutton> button to define a new filter. 
	Once you have designed your filters, you can edit, test, and delete 
	selected filters using the <guibutton>Edit...</guibutton>, 
	<guibutton>Test...</guibutton>, and <guibutton>Delete</guibutton> 
	buttons, respectively. All the filters displayed in the list will be 
	automatically saved along with your database and will be available 
	with subsequent sessions of &app;. </para>
	
	<para>Clicking the <guibutton>Add...</guibutton> button invokes the 
	following <guilabel>Define filter</guilabel> dialog: </para>
	
 	<!-- ==== Figure: Define filter dialog ==== -->
	<figure id="cfe-df-fig"> 
	<title>Define filter dialog</title> 
	<screenshot><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata 
		fileref="figures/cfe-df.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	<textobject> 
	<phrase>Shows Define filter dialog. </phrase>
	</textobject></mediaobject></screenshot></figure>
	<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

	<para> Type the name for your new filter into the 
	<guilabel>Name</guilabel> field. Enter any comment that would help you
	identify this filter in the future into the <guilabel>Comment</guilabel>
	field. Add as many rules to the <guilabel>Rule list</guilabel> as you
	would like to your filter using <guibutton>Add...</guibutton> button. 
	Check <guilabel>Return values that do not match the filter rules
	(invert)</guilabel> to negate the filter rule (e.g. inverting "has a
	common ancestor with I1" rule will match everyone who does not have a
	common ancestor with that person). If the filter has more than one rule, 
	select one of the <guilabel>Rule operations</guilabel>. This allows you
	to choose whether all rules must apply, only one (either) rule must 
	apply, or exactly one (either) rule must apply, in order for the filter 
	to generate a match. If your filter has only one rule, this selection 
	has no effect. </para>
	
	<para> Clicking the <guibutton>Add...</guibutton> button invokes the 
	following <guilabel>Add Rule</guilabel> dialog:</para>

 	<!-- ==== Figure: Add Rule dialog ==== -->
	<figure id="cfe-ar-fig"> 
	<title>Add Rule dialog</title> 
	<screenshot><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata 
		fileref="figures/cfe-ar.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
	<textobject> 
	<phrase>Shows Add Rule dialog. </phrase>
	</textobject></mediaobject></screenshot></figure>
	<!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->
	
	<para>The pane on the left-hand side displays available filter rules 
        arranged by their categories in an expandable tree. For detailed filter 
        rule reference, see <xref linkend="append-filtref"/>. Click on the 
        arrows to fold/unfold the appropriate category.  Select the rule 
        from the tree by clicking on its name. The right-hand side displays 
        the name, the description, and the values for the currently selected 
        rule. Once you are satisfied with your rule selection and its values, 
        click <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to add this rule to the rule list 
        of the currently edited filter. Clicking <guibutton>Cancel</guibutton>
        will abort adding the rule to the filter. </para>
        
        <para> Note that a filter you've already designed may be used as a rule
	for another filter. This gives you nearly infinite flexibility in
	custom-tailoring your selection criteria that can be later used in 
	most of the exports, reports and some of the tools (such as comparing
	individual events). </para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

 	<varlistentry><term>Generate SoundEx codes</term>
	<listitem><para>This utility generates SoundEx codes for the names of
	people in the database. Please visit the <ulink 
	url="http://www.archives.gov/research_room/genealogy/census/soundex.html" 
	type="http">NARA Soundex Indexing page</ulink> to learn more about 
	Soudex Indexing System.
	</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

 	<varlistentry><term>Relationship calculator</term>
	<listitem><para>This utility calculates the relationship between 
	two people from the database. 
	</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

 	<varlistentry><term>Verify the database</term>
	<listitem><para>This utility allows you to verify the database based 
	on the set of criteria specified by you. This tool is different from 
	the previously described Check tool in the following. The Check tool
	detects inconsistencies in the database structure. The Verify tool, 
	however, is detecting the records that do not satisfy your particular 
	criteria. </para>

	<para>For example, you may want to make sure that nobody in your 
	database had children at the age of 98. Based on common sense, such 
	a record would indicate an error. However, it is not a consistency 
	error in the database. Besides, someone might have a child at the of 
	98 (albeit this rarely happens). The Verify tool will display 
	everything that violates your criteria so that you can check whether 
	the record is erroneous or not. The ultimate decision is yours.
	</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	</variablelist>

     </sect2>

    </sect1>

</chapter>
